Thank you, Chairman.
獲得通過。
反對嘅請舉手。
有冇委員想發言？
第二至六及八條。
如果冇委員發言。
經修正的第一七及九條。
我認為議題獲得在席委員以過半數贊成，我宣佈修正案獲得通過。
我現在向各位提出嘅待決議題係第二至六及八條納入本條例草案，贊成嘅請舉手。
如果冇委員發言，我現在向各位提出嘅代決議題係律政司司長動議嘅修正案，予以通過，贊成嘅請舉手。
我認為議題獲得在席委員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。第一七及九條律政司司長。
我會先處理冇修正案嘅條文。現在我向各位提出嘅待議議題係以下條文納入二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案。
二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案，本會現在成為全體委員會就條例草案嘅辯論同埋表決安排，委員可參閲講稿附錄。
主席已 moved the amendments to the clauses set out just now. The amendments to those clauses are set out in the paper distributed to members. I've already explained the purposes of the amendments earlier today. The Bills Committee has examined the above amendments and did not raise any objections. I urge members to pass these amendments.
反對嘅請舉手。
全體委員會現在回覆為立法會。
我認為議題獲得在席委員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。
我現在向各位提出嘅代決議題係經修正嘅第一七及九條納入本條例草案，贊成嘅請舉手。