We have.
履行其議員嘅職責。
The secretary had not yet recover the monies.
有效未有效完成宣誓前，並冇展開。
to pay for their legal啊proceedings, legal costs.
The second item is to consider the request from梁國雄、劉小麗，and姚崇賢。
直至到相關嘅司法程序完結之後咧，我哋就會展開法律追討嘅行動。
The commission will commence the recovery action in court after the conclusion of the CFA legal proceedings.
After discussion, the commission has maintained its position that the remuneration and advances should be recovered in full.
嘅誒挑戰咧，行管會自會考慮啊負擔佢哋嘅訴訟費用。咁行管會考慮依三位議員咧喺在。
The first item is the recovery of members' remuneration and advance operation fund from Mr. Leung and Miss Yao.
前嘅決定，應向兩人全數追回款項。咁秘書處至今咧都未收到任何啊依啲回收嘅款項。咁經過討論之後咧，行管會決定。
行管會嘅現行政策咧，如果議員係因為喺立法會或者其下嘅委員會嘅程序中履行立法會議員嘅而引起嘅法律誒。
故係不適用於政策裏邊嘅範圍。咁經過行管會嘅討論同埋投票之後咧，行管會係唔會支付相關嘅費用。我用英文講一講咧。
第二件事咧就係三位議員，包括梁國雄、劉小麗同姚松炎咧，係要求恆管會啊承擔佢哋宣誓有關嘅司法程序嘅一切法律啊費用嘅事咧，根據。
啊！大家好。啊，行管會今早開咗會嘅，咁其中有兩件事就我想講講嘅。第一就係啊，梁仲恆同尤慧晶啊兩位回收佢哋嘅酬金同埋預支嘅營運資金一件事咧，行管會咧係會維持較早之。
係噉樣。
expenses.
secondary to.
誒，要揾兩隻經濟。
Do you think that will take a long time?
renew the money that.
hoping to take the case to court for final appeal.
咁但係而家佢哋被告嘅時候，就好似冇受到幫助唔到。
我諗其實最緊要就係佢係咪履行立法會。
我哋徵詢法律意見，係一號係有足夠嘅理據去。
可以用誒公房，跟住誒分供啊，轉接你嘅時候都可以有誒分誒八百蚊。
誒，即係維維持翻個原本其實係一號開始計起你哋嗰個酬金，咁其實我諮詢過，即係作進一步諮詢過法律意見，係咪？
誒追追回嗰啲款項，但係有啲意見咧，即係關於話三級店員誒攞立法會嘅錢打官司，有啲意見都覺得話政府去打官司。
As the three members are not discharging their legal duties in the present case, after discussion and voting, the commission decide not to accede to the members' request.
According to the Commission's prevailing policy, where individual members are involved in judicial proceedings arising from their discharge of legal duties in proceedings of legal or its committees, the Commission may consider bearing their legal.
嘅職責噉，但係當佢未有有效宣誓嗰陣時咧，啊，佢係咪係立法會議員咧？噉我哋經過詳細嘅討論同埋投票咧，都覺得係誒，行管會係唔需要啊，支付佢哋嘅費用。噉嘅誒。
今次。
有啲咩？
誒。
後面。
即係做部車。
好似真係話唔到。
成呢個政府。
was given to.
甚至雖然但。
但係認為佢哋嘅心。
就維持原判啦，咁其實係。
啲反對嘅聲音，同埋。
Court of Final Appeal， we just have to wait until a decision， you know， by the Court of Final Appeal being handed down， and then we will start recovering。
啊，或者中審庭接受咗，然後維持原判咧，之後噉我哋就會誒展開個法律程序。嗰個法律程序當然係有啊唔同嘅步驟啦。咁到時我哋會一步步行嘅。
但係，decision is very clear. We will you know start recovering the money after all proceedings been you know done. So we need to respect their rights to go to.
啊！嗱，第一樣嘢就誒，依樣嘢我哋冇投票嘅，唔需要投票啊。咁所以誒，大家經過討論咧，都係維持原判啦。咁究竟誒將來係點樣咧，都係要誒一步步嚟啦。咁而家只係話，如果誒終審庭係維持原判嘅時候。
噉樣佢先成。
我哋開個meeting。
但係立法會本身嚟講，
啊！They still have to.
咁但係你又唔畀錢佢哋去集，即係用咧。
可以生翻去讀，咁其實呢個決定真係。
議員係當時雖然可能有啲爭議，但係當時。
啊！立法會秘書長同埋。
同埋我微小上已經確定咗佢係有效嘅，即係阿小麗同埋。
So, since in your opinion they're not properly sworn in at the.
They run to the same problem of certain government officials not answering the questions.
OK，咁依一個你哋即係去睇睇誒法院嘅判決就寫得好清楚啦。
我只係一個行政上係監視嘅啫，究竟佢係咪有效翻啱使咧？最終都係要法庭去判決嘅。
誒嗱喺喺喺喺唔係誒誒個誒法庭嘅判決都寫得好清楚嘅。
咪咪立法會議員咯，嚇！咁而家個爭拗點就係佢係咪議員喺嗰個時候？咁但係即係經過討論咧，啊，我哋認為啊，佢係唔符合我哋而家行管會嘅既定嘅政策。三個議員當中係。
誒唔係奇怪嘅，其實就係誒政府去誒司法複核佢哋，或者同佢哋誒提出訴訟咧，就係講佢係十月十二號佢宣誓個時間嗰一刻。但係如果佢未有完成到一個有效嘅宣誓咧，噉佢。
Members, when they you know ask question.
To government official, this is for them to answer. OK，好唔該曬。
no, I have no opinion whether they have properly sworn in or not. It's the court have to decide whether they are properly sworn in or not. Okay, and I cannot you know answer on behalf of government how would government treat the four.