主席。
拒絕強制執行。
並唔違反香港嘅公共政策。
法案委員會大體上支持條例草案。
二仲裁裁決嘅強制執行及登記。
因此，現時嘅法律喺呢方面並唔完全清晰。
辯論終止待續，條例草案交由內務委員會處理。
法國法案委員會喺進行審議期間，曾集中討論數個方面。
主要嘅包括一知識產權嘅定義同知識產權可否付諸仲裁。
首先，任何有爭議嘅事項是否可以付諸仲裁，應該喺展開仲裁之前釐清。
本人僅以二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案委員會主席嘅身份，彙報法案委員會嘅審議工作。
香港直至目前亦都冇關於知識產權爭議可否以仲裁方式解決嘅權威性判決。
然而，香港法例第六零九章嘅仲裁條例並冇針對知識產權爭議可否以仲裁解決嘅具體條文。
政府當局為消除疑慮，建議釐清任何知識產權爭議，均可藉仲裁解決，而強制執行隨之產生嘅仲裁裁決。
本會恢復二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案嘅二讀辯論。條例草案委員會主席廖長江議員就委員會報告向本會發言。廖長江議員。
屆時喺處理根據《仲裁條例》第十部強制執行仲裁裁決時，有關仲裁決咧，將不會僅因其涉及知識產權爭議而基於不能藉仲裁解決或違反公共政策嘅理由喺香港遭。
法案委員會拆息。
註冊或存在嘅知識產權。
政府當局亦曾考慮，在於。
三條例草案是否影響保障競爭？
某世界貿易組織協定中有關知識產權爭議嘅寬鬆定義。
該些例子係因為喺諮詢過程中收到一啲持份者嘅意見而加入嘅。
以及四以仲裁代替訴訟所節省嘅時間和費用，以下我會簡單展述。
《議義》嘅第一零三B條再列多個非進列式嘅知識產權嘅例子，以界定知識產權一詞。
因此，法案委員會要求政府當局説明採用非進列式嘅例子，以界定知識產權一詞嘅立法原意同理據。
政府當局引用非進列式嘅例子，為知識產權作界定，以便提供彈性，容納將來可能出現嘅新嘅知識產權。
鑑於其他司法管轄區嘅知識產權可能以不同名稱表述，或以不同嘅形式保護，加上知識產權係個發展中嘅領域。
該等非進列式嘅例子中嘅部分詞語，例如專利、商標、版權及工業知識等，其涵義在本港其他條例之中已有明確界定。
政府當局表示，新定嘅《第103B條》所使用嘅知識產權嘅寬鬆定義，符合促進喺香港更廣泛使用知識產權仲裁嘅政策意向。
政府當局表示，擬議嘅《第103B條》一條提供非進列式嘅一啲常見嘅知識產權例子，係為咗向知識產權仲裁嘅使用者提供更多指引。
法案委員會亦闡釋，政府當局預期喺香港進行盡裁嘅爭議，不僅涵蓋喺香港註冊或存在嘅知識產權，亦涵蓋喺其他司法管轄區。
此外，政府當局又澄清，而以嘅第一零三B括弧一條A至J段所列嘅詞語係按其一般通用嘅意思使用，其含義並不受香港其他法例再有嘅相關定義所限制。
政府當局解釋。
政府當局補充。
此外，法案委員會亦闡釋，仲裁只係解決爭議嘅方法之一。
對保密性嘅任何損害，均可能影響香港作為主要國際仲裁中心嘅地位。
政府當局又強調，不論喺本地或國際層面，保密性係仲裁嘅其中一個主要特點。
保密性亦係爭議各方寧可選擇以仲裁方式，而非法院訴訟解決爭議嘅其中一個重要原因。
當事人亦可利用紐約公約下嘅機制，喺全球超過一百五十個紐約公約大約國強制執行仲裁裁決。
若所涉及爭議嘅係牽涉多個司法管轄區嘅大型知識產權項目，仲裁會係一個對當事人有利嘅選擇。
香港已在其仲裁法例中就保密性加入明文規定，可見保密性喺香港嘅仲裁機制中特別重要。
並表示仲裁裁決只對仲裁各方具有約束力，對於沒有參與有關程序嘅任何第三者並無約束力。
政府當局亦研究咗三十個司法管轄區，關於知識產權爭議嘅可仲裁性，以及是否披露知識產權仲裁裁決嘅做法。
仲裁嘅好處包括提供單一平台於當事人解決爭議事宜，而當事人有自由委任具備相關專長嘅仲裁員。
再者，由於仲裁裁決只對仲裁各方具有效力，加上仲裁須與保密嘅性質，故此不會規定必須把仲裁裁決作出登記。
基於以上原因，政府當局認為香港不宜強制規定必須披露知識產權仲裁裁決，並要求將裁決喺香港嘅知識產權註冊處進行登錄。
就法案委員會詢問條例草案獲通過後，當事人是否需要把有關嘅仲裁裁決喺相關嘅政府登記處登記？政府當局表示不需要。
當局注意到有進行知識產權爭議裁決嘅司法管轄區嘅一般做法係並沒有要求強制披露或登錄，只對仲裁各方具有效力嘅知識產權仲裁裁決。
佢哋亦可透過合同安排，以保障佢哋嘅權益。
並要求政府當局徵詢香港競爭事務委員會嘅意見。
呢個情況與其他司法管轄區嘅知識產權法係一致嘅。
亦不會影響香港競爭事務委員會調查同執法嘅權力。
政府當局認為條例草案不會在競爭法律方面引起任何實質問題。
重要嘅係，只對仲裁各方具有效力嘅仲裁裁決，並不影響第三者嘅權利。
政府當局又表示，假如法院認為仲裁裁決導致潛在嘅反競爭協議得以施行。
鑑於仲裁協議及仲裁裁決需予保密，法案委員會對條例草案是否足以保障競爭表示關注。
有違競爭條例嘅規定，法院可以基於公共政策嘅理由，撤銷有關裁決，或拒絕強制執行該裁決。
佢哋可針對仲裁一方即知識產權擁有人，而喺法院程序或相關知識產權嘅註冊處處長職前爭取其權利。
政府當局重申，仲裁一種競爭中立嘅程序，使用仲裁或者係仲裁及仲裁裁決嘅保密性質，本身並不反競爭。
知識產權交易各方一般都係對市場有認識嘅商家，預計佢哋與知識產權擁有人訂立商業交易之前，會進行調查及或進職審查。
此外，二嘅知識產權仲裁製度亦屬競爭中立，該制度唔會影響第三方嘅權利或有關競爭事宜嘅香港法律下嘅法院或主管當局嘅權力。
此外，當局亦已請香港競爭事務委員會以書面提出意見，而該委員會亦同意政府嘅意見，認為條例草案及其對仲裁程序嘅影響屬競爭中立。
政府當局又澄清，根據香港法律，知識產權擁有人一般可以自由畀他人給予知識產權特許，而無需以相同條款向所有人給予作特許，甚或無需給予特許。
亦唔會喺競爭條例第六一九章下引起任何反競爭問題。無論如何，仲裁同競爭法例嘅制度咧已經有足夠保障，可處理喺仲裁中產生嘅有關競爭嘅關注。
有冇議員想發言？
政府當局解釋。
法案委員會拆釋。
以法律費用而言，訴訟嘅平均費為。
透過仲裁解決爭議，平均需時稍稍多於一年。
透過法院聆訊解決爭議，平均需時三至三年半。
法案委員會不已就條例草案動議任何修正案，主席。
於獻報刊登嘅月份之後嘅第七個月嘅首日生效。
權擁有人必須給予所有商業夥伴或特許持有人同等嘅對待。
根據世界知識產權組織二零一三年一項有關解決技術交易爭議嘅調查嘅結果。
法案委員會曾關注到，以仲裁代替訴訟解決知識產權爭議，是否能減省開支和提高效率？
四十七萬五千美元，至稍為高於八十五萬美元，而仲裁嘅費用包括仲裁員嘅費用，平均稍高，稍為高於四十萬美元。
條例草案嘅立法原意之一係提升香港作為亞太區主要國際及解決爭議服務中心，以及作為區內首屈一指嘅知識產權貿易中心嘅地位。
當局強調公平競爭環境，需要求維持公平市場競爭。但呢個公平競爭環境一般並沒有把坦誠責任施加於知識產權擁有人，以致其必須向所有人以相同程度披露所有資料，亦唔要求知識產。
法案委員會拆識政府當局將會就條例草案動議，全體委員會審議階段修正案，使仲裁條例新定嘅一誒第十一A部有關知識產權嘅仲裁新定嘅第一零三J條除外，能緊接喺修訂條例。
另外，政府當局以修訂條例草案第九括回二條，將新加入咗紐約公約嘅安哥拉加加入仲裁紐約公約第約方零嘅附表，對上述嘅修訂法案委員會並無異議。有關嘅詳情已在屬於報告中。
冇。
The New York Convention.
我會也表達我的感謝，給發展機構們的寶貴意見和支持。
如果冇，我而家請律政司司長答辯，之後辯論即告結束。結束，司長。
Moreover, it's also considered that the bill is consistent with the competition ordinance from an enforcement perspective.
Are competition neutral, and that confidentiality of arbitration is unlikely by itself to be inconsistent with the competition ordinance, Cap 619.
During discussions of the bills committee, some members raised the question of whether confidentiality of arbitration process and of arbitral awards would give rise to competition concerns.
We believe that the amendments on arbitrability of IPR disputes will help attract more parties to resolve their IPR disputes through arbitration in Hong Kong, and facilitate the enforcement of related arbitral awards in Hong Kong.
As I pointed out when introducing the bill into this council last December, the ordinance presently does not have any specific provision dealing with the arbitrability of IPR disputes, and there is no authoritative judgement in Hong Kong on the subject.
since confidentiality of arbitration is not by itself anti-competitive, whether disclosure or record of IPR arbitral awards should be required must be considered carefully in light of relevant wider public policy considerations.
主席，《的 arbitrations amendment bill 2016》的Bill已經被詳細審查，由議員委員會主席馬汀·奈主持。我會利用這個機會表達我們對馬汀·奈及所有議員委員會成員的感謝，感謝他們在審查該法案時的辛勤工作。
The main objective of the bill is to amend the arbitration ordinance, Cap 609, the ordinance, so as to clarify that disputes over intellectual property rights, which I shall call the IPR disputes, can be resolved through arbitration, and that it is not contrary to the public policy of Hong Kong to enforce arbitral awards in.
涉及IPRs，The bill also proposed to amend the schedule to the arbitration parties to New York Convention Order 609 Capital A to update the list of parties to the 1958 Convention on the recognition and enforcement of foreign arbitral awards， which is also known as
政府已於近年來向法案委員會詳細解釋相關發展問題，並充分考慮法案委員會成員、業界及香港競爭委員會的意見。總言之，競爭委員會同意該法案及其對仲裁程序的影響。
我 wish to take this opportunity to reiterate that the bill seeks to amend the ordinance so as to clarify that IPR disputes can be resolved through arbitration for the purposes of facilitating the conduct of intellectual property IP arbitration and the enforcement of related arbitral awards.
在香港，The Bill does not seek to alter the substantive legal rights of the parties to any arbitration or any third parties, the position of competition law in Hong Kong, or the power of the courts or competition authorities in relation to competition issues under the laws of Hong Kong.
New York Convention Order。
Ordinance in the Gazette.
這些包括，第一，的重視保密性在香港的仲裁製度。
by virtue of clause one bracket two of the bill, the relevant amendment will come into operation on the date of gazette.
任何 erosion of confidentiality may prejudice Hong Kong's position as a leading international arbitration centre.
第二， arbitral awards in general only have inter partes effect, which means that the legal rights of third party will not be affected.
主席，我將會推動一連串的委員會階段修正案。稍後，法案委員會審查了擬議的CSA，並未提出任何反對意見。我將簡要説明擬議的CSA如下。
Having taken into account all relevant factors, the government considers it not necessary or appropriate to require mandatory disclosure of IPR arbitral awards or the recordal with IPR registries in Hong Kong.
Further, we have considered the practice of 30 jurisdictions. Based on our survey, we note that the general practice in these jurisdictions is that mandatory disclosure or record of IPR arbitral awards with inter partes effect is not required.
In other words, if the amendment ordinance is passed by the council and gazetted within this month, i.e., June 2017, the above mentioned legislative amendments relating to IP arbitration will come into operation on 1 January 2018.
CSA to clause 1 bracket 3 and related CSAs to clause 7 of the bill, to the effect that relevant amendments will commence on the first day of the seventh month immediately following the month in which the amendment ordinance is published in the Gazette.
這些係，有 safeguards for third-party interests under the existing arbitration and legal regimes. Third party may also seek to protect their interests by conducting investigation or due diligence, or by negotiating suitable contractual provisions.
Confidentiality is what, locally or internationally, often one of the key reasons why parties prefer to use arbitration as opposed to court litigation to resolve disputes. In the case of Hong Kong, such confidentiality is expressly provided for in section 18 of the ordinance.
According to clause 1 bracket 3 of the bill, the amendments connecting IP arbitration, i.e. part two of the bill, except the new section 103 capital J, are to come into operation on 1 October 2017, rather than on the day of publication of the amend.
反對嘅請舉手。
to support the second reading of the bill and the amendments that I will move at the subsequent committee stage. Thank you, President.
二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案，本會現在成為全體委員會修條例。
我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。
The established policy of the Department of Justice is to encourage the use of arbitration to resolve civil and commercial disputes.
我現在向各位提出嘅待決議題係二零一六年仲裁修訂條例草案，予以閲讀贊成嘅，請舉手。
To further consolidate Hong Kong's status as a leading centre for international legal and dispute resolution services in the Asia-Pacific region, the Department of Justice has been reviewing the arbitration regime of Hong Kong from time to time, and will also consider improvement to the ordinance.
The underlying policy intent of this deferred commencement provision, as originally drafted, is to allow the IP arbitration community a period of around six months after the passage of the bill to prepare for commencement of development amendments. To give effect to this policy intent, I will move.
separately, since the government introduced the bill, Angola has recently acceded to the New York Convention, with effect from 4 June 2017. Therefore, I will move another CSA to amend Clause 9 bracket 2 of the bill in order to add Angola to the schedule to the arbitration parties to.
The government believes that developing amendments to the bill will further consolidate Hong Kong's competitiveness as a leading international arbitration centre and reinforce Hong Kong's edge over other jurisdictions in the region in resolving IP disputes. President, with these remarks, I urge members.