好啊，多謝啊，Mr. Blanche Flower啊嘅諒解。咁咧就我哋咧而家恢復我哋委員會嘅會議，咁再請誒你繼續發言，表達你嘅意見。
多謝主席。
Where we're talking about the jury trial, it is, as many of you know, a very important common law right.
and it was a common law right up to just past the Second World War, and as I said, various high courts, courts of final appeal in many jurisdictions, and leading jurists have spoken about the importance to individuals of a trial by jury. It's the guard.
憲法的自由， garanties the sound administration of justice, protects individuals against oppressive laws.
那，right。
at the present situation.
是 enjoyed only when the DPP decides by choice of venue that it should be tried by jury. Apart from certain offences that have to be tried by jury.
The paper prepared by the DPP makes numerous references to a case of Lily Chiang.
Now.
我 wouldn't want members to read too much into that case. That was a case of judicial review, and all it said is that the decision by the DPP to decide a trial in the district court was not unreasonable in the usual judicial review sense.
它 did not and one can see the judgments address the wider issues of the importance of trial by jury. So one can't read too much into that case.
在材料那隻提供給成員在六月二零一零年，我們的律師協會有啲提及到。
重要性 of trial by jury, but here we have a situation in its application by the DPP's discretion. We have a case, a recent case of money laundering in the district court of some four hundred million dollars.
我 was recently involved with a conspiracy case of two billion dollars tried in the district court.
我最近涉及一宗涉及六名專業人士。
The Shanghai Land Case lawyers, financial people, tried in the district court where they're.
honesty, their credibility was key. Ultimately, thankfully, they were all acquitted in the court of final appeal. But one just shakes their head sometimes, wondering why some cases are in the district court.
and and I say not only from a defence perspective but certainly the public has an interest in the proper adjudication of cases. Now, over the last four years there have been discussions between the bar and the DPP and to put it in a very simple
term it has been over disappointing that.
many of the matters taken up by the DPP, some have been reflected in the code, but there are still numerous inadequacies, and we made that known to the DPP in January after the new revised code came out.
所以， as matters presently stand， the bar association and I don't know what the position for the law society is not satisfied with the present code.
I can go a number of reasons. There is no indication.
of the importance of jury trials. Now, this code is not only for prosecutors; it's for the public. It should give guidance to the public, and dealing with prosecutors, very often inexperienced prosecutors who themselves have little or no experience with trial by jury, gives no indication of the importance of this.
Trial by jury.
The.
嗯。
Present code repeats many of the points in the earlier guidelines.
它 does set out factors and you'll see that present code in enclosure number two.
Now whether members have it before you, eight point four.
A、B、C、H和J都已經在之前的碼中出現過，所以它只是被放在不同的段落裡重新標記。
But when you look at A to I， it is a mere statement. There's no guidance， no indication， no examples of how it should be applied.
嗯。
what it leads to is arbitrariness and lack of consistency in decision making. So any prosecutor looking at this wouldn't see how various factors are to be weighed in favour of a jury trial or a district court trial.
Matters of particularly dishonesty, which are very important in many cases, are not specifically addressed.
and there is no addressing the very important matter of the
representations from defendants. Now in the DPP's paper, it says.
as far as representations in paragraph nine four, representations are not ignored. Code does not intend and should not make one feel inhibited. Well.
如果 representations are important, it should be in the code. When you look at guidelines in the UK DPP guidelines, they are thick documents.
thick documents which give considered and detailed reference as to how decisions are made.
not only for the public but for individuals. Now, what?
The what the paper doesn't appreciate and mention is that in January of 2013, the European Court of Human Rights ruled in a case which involved the Attorney General of Malta deciding which court a person should be tried in.
和的決定會ffect the punishment. now, albeit it wasn't a matter of whether judge-alone trial or jury trial, but the the importance of that decision was that it held it was unlawful under the Article Seven of the European Convention on Human Rights, which
finds its counterpart in Article 12 of Hong Kong's Bill of Rights. It found that without guidance, without any indication in law, that it gave rise to arbitrariness.
And so, for those reasons and more, Madam Chairman, the Bar Association is not satisfied with the present code. We do not believe that it has moved the matter substantially from where we started our discussions four years ago, and that's why.
我會邀請這個委員會，主席女士，將這個問題帶回議程，或許在秋天，以便成員可以得到一份文件，詳細説明巴爾的立場，以便研究。非常感謝。
Blanchflower，咁咧就提出咗好多嘅好好嘅啊論點嚇。咁而家咧，我哋就將嗰個時間交畀大家委員。咁咧，蘇即係到而家咧，就只係得一位議員先舉手，係咁咧就有兩位議員，三位。誒，我每一位咧先畀。
四分鐘，咁咧亦都誒，盡量希望咧係可以，我都希望可以寬鬆少少。咁第一位咧就係郭榮亨議員。
多謝主席。主席，誒，我想問問大律師公會嘅誒誒代表啦，或者我用英文啦。誒，Mr. Blanchflower，誒，You you pointed out just now that the prosecution code，誒，the bar is obviously not happy with the way it has been revised。我講緊about paragraph，誒，paragraphs eight in the code。
Could could you give some perhaps recommendations or examples in which you think the code could be further improved?
And to address the concerns you you raised just now.
Yes, in in all the matters that we see set out in paragraph eight.
first of all， we would。
urge the DPP to set out in his code.
In a summary form or in some details, and there's there's no there should be no inhibition as to size to reinforce and put it clear what trial by jury is and its importance in the common law system, so that there.
年輕 Prosecutors and the public can see the importance of trial by jury, so we know what we're talking about.
So to set out basic principles of the fundamental importance of trial by jury as a right. Yes, and and just to to to repeat what final courts of appeal, what leading jurists have talked about the trial by jury, so that prosecutors have.
那firmly in their mind.
understand係啊，楊村元會唔會有啲咩回應？楊村元。
誒多謝主席。但就住呢一點咧，我都誒聽過頭先啊，Mr. Branchflower講話關於我哋香港嘅判例，我哋唔應該誒讀太多，因為咧佢哋只係一啲誒judicial review嘅判例，或者就住為咗個記錄起見。
我都想讀幾段出嚟，因為嗰個判決咧唔係淨係關於話嗰個決定係咪合理嘅，亦都正正就係講到喺香港嘅範疇裏邊，究竟有冇一個選擇，或者有冇一個去？
由陪審員去決去誒審訊呢一個權利嗱。首先喺初審嘅時候，原審法官咁講喺第一段開宗明義講就係。
There does not exist in Hong Kong any absolute right to trial by jury, nor any mechanism by which a person to be tried of an indictable offence may elect to be so tried. The decision as to whether an indictable offence be tried in Hong Kong in the court of first instance by a judge and jury or in the district court by
Judge alone is the prerogative of the Secretary for Justice。嗱，呢個係原審去到上訴庭嘅時候，誒當時嘅馬道立法官，現在我哋嘅最終高等法誒最誒終審庭嘅首席法官，佢咁講喺第一頁，喺第一段。
However, I ought to make clear at the outset that these appeals are not about whether a right to a jury trial exists in Hong Kong. It is accepted that there is no right or entitlement as such. It also ought to be made clear that while the applicant wishes to have a trial by
同樣嘅説話咧，喺誒。
馬法官嘅第嘅判詞第廿四段咧，亦都有同樣嘅講法。跟住去到終審庭嘅時候咧，終審庭當時嘅誒李國梁首席大法官喺第九段亦都係咁講。
as is rightly accepted by the African, it is clear that there is no right to trial by jury in Hong Kong。嗱個問題就係當然。
喺一九五三年，香港未有區域法院法例之前，香港嗰個普通法有冇話承認香港有呢個陪審團審訊權利呢樣嘢係另一回事。但係自從一九五三年，香港嘅法律同埋香港嘅機制已經完全唔同咗，去到現。
在基於基本法、基於人權法、基於我哋最高法庭所講嘅嘅善識，香港已經唔係再好似其他嘅誒普通法國家噉樣去就住呢一個權利嘅嘅唔已經有唔完全唔同嘅睇法喺呢一個大前提之下，誒，我聽到Mr. Blanchflower講話，我哋喺
個誒prosecution code裏邊應該寫翻誒呢個普通法裏邊嘅一啲精神出嚟，但係呢啲普通法而家香港已經唔再適用嘅時候，我有好大嘅保留。究竟將一啲唔再適用嘅普通法法規喺個誒個prosecution code度重新寫出嚟，個用處喺邊度咧？誒，呢個係我。
我誒最主要嘅回應好啊！我哋畀第二位議員發問先嚇，就係阿謝偉俊議員。
主席，我諗。
誒。
民主制度咧，就。
好講話，希望有個即係。
普選啦！
咁雖然咧就冇咩真冇咩假嘅，即係冇咩叫終極嘅。總之就係一個方向，一個方向感，好似一個北極星噉，我哋朝嗰個方向去。
咁司法制度咧就公平審訊就應該係呢個北極星嚟，意思就係話咧，我哋雖然咧就每一個國家嘅制度可能唔同，但係目標都始終向住公平審訊嘅方向進發。咁呢個大前提，我相信咧就阿楊主任唔會即係誒否認啦，或者唔會誒誒覺得係唔啱。
睇翻喺一九五二年咧，就我哋設設立嗰個地方法院嘅時候咧，喺文件裏面有介紹到啦，就亦都係由於係一九九七年嘅時候有個文件介紹點解即係關於呢個誒裁判審裁判團嘅審訊應唔應應否被誒納入呢個地方法院嘅時候咧？
都曾經係講過咧，就其中一個最大原因，當時喺五二年入呢誒制定呢個地方法院法例嘅時候咧，唔採用陪審團制度嘅最大原因，就因為擔心唔夠陪審陪審員啊。而香港呢個陪審員制度，大家都知道，應該好唔同咧，就係我哋有個英文嘅能力嘅要求。
呢個係好多其他其他國家，包括英國係冇嘅。
咁當然，大家考慮翻當時咧睇重食飯咧，因為真係識英文嘅人或者有資格做陪審員嘅人係唔多啦。但係似乎隨著九七之後咧，嗰個審訊嘅語言改變咗啦。誒，我哋香港嘅教水平唔同咗啦，咁變咗當時呢個噉嘅顧慮咧，係喺某程度上係少咗，甚至係冇嘅。咁所以呢個背。
背景咧，我哋希望可以即係大家都誒瞭解多少少。咁翻嚟我誒另外咧，基本法裏邊咧，剛才誒有提及過嘅問題咧，我想理解下，除咗話係喺基本法冇話到明咧有一個選擇陪審團嘅權利之外，
現行嘅基本法八十一條同八十六條有冇任何障礙令到我哋唔能夠向前行，係推動咗地方法院嘅陪審團咧？我睇到八十一同八十六條嘅文字似乎就冇呢個好明顯嘅一個障礙喺度嘅，只不過係保留翻個陪審團制度，保留翻香港司法制度，但係冇話唔可以有任何改善，特別係。
同一個我剛才講嘅向北極星嘅方向行行前一步，一個公平嘅審訊嘅制度，咁呢方面。
噉我真係想問佢兩個問題咧，希望誒局方如果係暫時未能夠有答案咧，都希望可以下一次，特別係我都同意啊，Mr. Flower嘅建議咧，仲我哋誒張生咧揸嚟睇下。第下一次要更加多資料嘅時候咧，可以係再去考慮呢個問題。但係兩個喺事實上嘅一啲嘅誒基礎，我可希望當局可以誒畀到以答案我哋嘅。
一就係。
誒，我哋有冇過往嘅關於誒一個地方法院相比起誒一個有陪審團制度嘅最高法院或者原審法庭？
嘅一個一個conviction rate一個定罪嘅一個記錄，有譬如話有法院幾多percent係conviction咧？high court jury有幾多percent係conviction？我想做一個比較。嗱，如果發近十年有、近五年有，我哋做一個比較。第二個數據，我想希望當我提供嘅就係話，如果我哋真係要將呢個陪審團制度推廣至地方法。
法院嘅話咧，喺嗰個實際可行上，特別喺嗰個誒仲費或者喺我哋個經營法院個費用方面咧，會有幾大一個負面嘅影響，或者個包袱咁呢個咧，我希望可以下一次有機會嘅時候咧，係當局提供埋噉，或者希望或者楊專賢可以先答答嗰個覺得個基本法係咪一個一個一個。
impediment或者一個obstacle，同我哋個個好楊主任係誒多謝主席誒幾樣嘢咧，第一。
就住基本法係咪有個impediment？
誒，我哋會分開兩個角度嚟睇。第一，我哋現在講嘅所謂權利咧，有我哋其實係講緊兩樣。第一就係去選擇以陪審團形式審訊呢一個權利，係一個選擇權。第二就係去接受陪審團審訊呢一個。
陪審團審訊嘅權利。
嗱就第一就住選擇呢個權利咧，其實誒有香港喺一九七七年已經有一個判例誒上訴庭嘅判例，係講咗其實由始到終咧喺普通法裏邊咧係冇選擇呢個權利嘅，選擇呢一方面係冇嘅。
誒而去而就住話陪審團制度之下去應信呢一個權利咧，誒香港正如頭先我上次解釋嗰個法律同埋嗰個整體情況咧，亦都變化好大。嗱喺呢個背景之下，我哋如果睇翻《基本法》，《基本法》第八十六條所講嘅咧，就係話。
話香港現行嘅陪審團嘅。
嗯。
制度或者呢個principle咧係保留嗱，若哥，我哋將呢個誒背景睇落去，一九九七年或者係基本法實施嘅當年咧，其實香港第一係冇陪審團，冇選擇陪審團審訊呢個制度，你冇呢個權利。第二，即使就住話。
喺陪審團制度面前接受審訊呢個權利都好咧。當時已經已經被呢個呢個五二年嘅誒立嘅地方法院嘅法嘅呢條法例咧係已經改變得好緊要。咁所以若果我哋將當一誒基本法第八十六條擺翻落去嗰陣時間嚟。
嚟睇咧，有一個睇法，可能可以就係話，至少。
喺嚴格法律嚟講咧，可以睇成就係話，只係當時嘅陪審團制度係保持不變。若果當時陪審團制度係A嘅話咧，要轉做B咧，有可能有一個憲法上嘅嘅嘅問題。呢個誒，我哋需要詳細研究。但係我睇咧，可以噉樣睇，可以噉樣誒考慮。
阿智議員頭先提到另一個問題，就係關於誒，若果將陪審團制度誒喺
區域法院實施所牽涉嘅包覆程序，咁呢啲咧以前曾經誒去討論過，但係現在要。
喺呢方面嘅資料咧，我我手頭上係冇嘅。噉啊，我諗謝謝議員頭先，你都你問嘅問題嘅時候都理解。但係就住你問到話嗰個conviction rate咧，我手頭上係有一啲資料嘅。咁其實我自己亦都計過啲數，嗰啲數誒，大家而家聽落去咧，其實可能會覺得。
係誒幾有啟發性嘅。
嗱，當然。
循住或者向住呢個公道審訊呢個北極星咧，作為大家大律師，作為我自己嘅專業，呢個係我自己終身追求。但係呢一個
公正嘅審訊嗰個形式係點樣咧？嗱，若果呢一個定罪率係任何嘅基準嘅話咧，我可以誒噉樣講。
喺區域法院，由二零零九年至到二零一三年呢五年期間。
嗰個定罪率嗱喺呢個定罪率咧，我係撇除咗認罪之後定罪，我純粹係講緊喺唔認罪之後嘅定罪率。
二零零九年至到二零一三年，區域法院分別係六十九點二、七十五點三、六十八點六、六十點二、九十啊，同埋七十九點八。
呢五年平均嘅唔認罪之後嘅定罪率咧，係七十點六二個percent。呢個係區域法院。
而就住原眾庭，原喺有陪審團制度之下，被告人不認罪之後而被定罪嘅，同樣五年嘅嘅嘅記錄咧，分別係零九年開始六十五點三。
七十一點七、七十二、六十九點六，同埋六十七點三，而平均數咧係六十九點一八。我再重複一次，區域法院嘅平均值係七十點六二。
袁仲庭係六十九點一八，其實相差係一點幾個百分點嘅啫。而就住整體嘅定罪率，嗱整體意思係即係話包括埋認罪嘅定罪率。啊，謝議員，我唔煩你嗰啲誒細字啦，細數字。而喺同樣嗰五年地方。
方法院個定罪率係九十三點一percent。
原仲庭係九十二點八八嘅percent，係少於一個百分比嘅相差。嗱，當然誒，我哋純粹睇啲百分點係有一個有一某程度上邊嘅誒參考價值，但係當然喺地方法院或者區域法院同埋誒原仲庭嘅審嘅刑事。
個案件個性質可能唔同，但係至少咧喺數字上就係噉樣睇到出嚟。好，誒跟住咧，我哋要畀阿蔣麗雲議員。
啊，唔該，主席。咁咧就誒，首先就喺啲文件裏邊咧就有提及到咧就蔣麗麗女士㗎。噉我喺呢度要講一講啦，蔣麗麗女士咧就係我嘅親戚。咁不過咧就啊，我係冇任何嘅利益誒牽涉在內嚇。再加上咧整件啊案。
件咧已經完結咗㗎啦，嚇！噉我亦都不過咧，我唔會係啊喺呢度會特別提有關佢嘅審判啊情況嘅內容嚇。咁咧，我倒係咧就即係係係啊想問咧就係。
啊！
我哋知道而家外國咧，即係都有好多先進嘅國家都有呢一個陪審團嘅制度。
咁咧就其實啊，我都好想聽下專員嘅諗法，即係點解嗰啲國家會有呢個陪審團嘅制度咧？咁
咁誒？
誒或者係專員，你可以用啲時間嚇。
復復我呢樣嘢嚇！好，楊專員。
誒當然喺。
我唔係，我唔敢講話冇陪審團制度嘅國家就誒並非先進，但係實際上就係大部分嘅先進國家咧係有陪審團制度，呢個我睇過，亦都係事實。
但係陪審團制度咧，有佢唔同國家，甚至話好似譬如話澳洲噉，唔同佢嘅省份都有佢唔同嘅運作模式。
喺無陪審團喺陪審團制度之下，究竟第一？
乜嘢罪或者乜嘢嘅審訊係？
必須。
或者可以喺陪審團席前去審訊，若果係可以嘅情況，究竟係邊一個去選擇嗰條控罪係喺陪審團席前去審訊，而呢個選擇權究竟係控方？
辯方，亦或係由法庭決定，特別當控辯。
正常情況誒得唔到共識嘅時候，法庭點判？甚至話法庭判嘅時候係咪都要聽完被告人嗰個選擇權？即使話選擇被被告人嘅選擇權係有整體嘅凌駕性嘅力嘅嘅力量。咁呢個呢一點咧都係好重。
重要嘅嗱，我不為言講喺唔同嘅國家咧，有佢哋嘅陪審團制度同埋佢哋運作模式，所以我要坐喺度同你哋講，我亦都唔會咁做，話陪審團制度係不可行嘅，係誒係誒畀被告人有選擇權係理論上係不可能嘅，我唔會噉。
講，但係個問題就係話，究竟應該點做，同埋喺我哋香港，自從一九五三年已經有呢一個區域法院同埋地方法院嘅呢一個制度之後，我哋現在經過咁多年，我哋嘅法庭制度同埋我哋嘅檢控制度已經有一定程度上邊，基於呢樣嘢嘅演變之後。
誒嗰個事情要假設有任何變化嘅時候，嗰個變化會係幾根本咧？噉。
我亦都可以，亦都可以講，就係任何呢方面變化咧，可以係非常根本嘅。點解咧？因為喺外國，佢哋好多時咧，誒，佢哋現在現行嘅陪審團制度都係已經經過多年冇間斷性嘅繼續噉樣去運作，佢哋就住唔同。
同嘅控罪嗰個。
定位啊，主席，我拖嚟下，我打斷下，主席，因為我得四分鐘，你講咗我三分鐘啊，主席。哦，對住，對唔住。嗱，其實我可以咁講，或或者我簡單噉樣再誒再誒總結就係誒正如我頭先講，係可行嘅。但係譬如話香港我哋要做嘅話咧，究竟會唔會現在有好多原本？
已經去，已經喺誒裁判處審嘅案件都會上咗高院去用一個陪審團制度咧。呢一啲我哋都要詳細考慮。好，我只想你畀畀畀多少時間你？畀多少時間？咁咧就誒，我只係想同阿專員講咧，其實我哋都睇到咧，咁而家好多一啲先進國家咧都係行緊呢個陪審團制。
度咁咧就誒，即係喺當然佢哋一定有佢哋嘅優勢啦，係咪噉就誒誒嘅優點在邊度咧？我相信啊，專員可能都會知道嘅。咁咧，我喺呢度唔詳盡講啦。咁咧，而另外咧就係誒。
啊，即係啊，好似譬如香港嘅誒，一路好多法律都係係係參考英國㗎嘛。咁而事實上，英國亦都有陪審團制度。據我所知咧，而家咧有時就算有人被懷疑係偷入一粒糖啊，都可以要求陪審團嘅制度嘅。
噉樣咧，另外咧就有一點咧，就係喺呢度咧，就有關啊呢個檢控守則嘅相關有啲摘錄啦。即係其實咧，就譬如話啊呢個八點四啦，咁咧就係檢控人員咧可以考慮，即係譬如話啊一。
一個人應該啊將係誒擺喺呢個誒裁判法院啦，或者區域法院啦，或者係甚至更高嘅，要去到咩法院咧？噉樣咁其實咧。
我相信啊，呢個最主要嘅指引好清晰咧，就係講緊咧，就係假如佢只係可能好細嘅罪，噉你咧就冇理由將佢擺喺高等法院啦，係咪嚇？咁即係誒，可能啊，裁判即係啊，法院就搞掂啦。咁而但係而。
但係，假如有人認為佢自己要求嘅，我去高等法院嚇，咁呢個情況係咪屬於一種特殊嘅情況？喺呢個情況係咪應該某方面要考慮下咧？咁？
咁另外咧，你啱啱即係即係提出嗰個八點三嗰度咧，就係誒有關基本法嘅第八十六條啦。咁嗰度咁咧就其實即係喺呢度咧，即係原在香港實行的陪審制度的原則予以保留。其實呢度好清楚咧。
就係原來實行緊嘅嘢，我哋唔好取消佢，就係噉。但係你增加嘅嘢，絕對咧成本基本法增加嘅嘢咧，係冇可能一日集落㗎。我哋而家每日喺度立法，都係每日增加嘅嘢入去嘅。
咁好似正如好似嗯，下終審庭大法官夏正民咧，亦都講過嘅，佢話啲嗯。
the article in question, article 86, speaks of the principle of trial by jury being maintained as previously practised in Hong Kong, but of course, as it was previously practised.
在香港，was according to specific factual circumstances then and those circumstances have changed. As previously practice, of course, goes to something more fundamental than the exigencies of any particular situation.
In history, for example, how many jurors there were in 1977, as opposed to how many jurors there are now. 拱內早。
喺一九七七年咧，當時司法界咧亦都係提及過有關呢個陪審團制度嘅，但係當時咧。
係估計，但係當時咧陪審團喺香港符合資格嘅咧，估計只係有兩萬幾人。
咁但係咧，今日去到二零一四年啦，噉我哋已經係遠遠超過呢一個數，估計已經超過六十萬人嘅。
咁所以喺符合資格嘅陪審團嘅人員之中咧，我覺得我哋即係亦都能夠符合咗呢一點。好，嚇我嚇。
咁咧就啊嗱，我自己都有問題跟進，咁因為咧頭先亦都有委員，我係畀到八分鐘，所以咧我知道大家都係誒我哋誒舉手嘅同事亦都唔多。嗱，我都有一個跟進，跟住請阿楊專員一並即係去回應我哋大律師公會嘅代表同埋各位委員嘅問題。嗱，首先咧我。
係誒，好同意啊，Mr誒Blanchflower，佢係我哋咧都係好願意將呢個事項咧會擺喺待議事項。頭先提嘅意見咧，我亦都會係誒誒會係誒接受嘅嗱。咁咧我自己咧就睇到阿楊專員頭先嘅答覆同埋咧好多關於陪審團嘅呢個意見啦嗱。首先咧講基本法八十。
六條，如果我哋睇翻《基本法》八十六條咧，據我所瞭解咧，佢係講緊咧，就係話我哋喺普通法嘅陪審團制度咧，係唔會因為迴歸呢一樣嘢去改變嘅。但係就唔等於我哋唔可以改善，亦都唔等於呢個制度咧係一成不變嘅。所以咧，我覺得係絕對咧喺。
我哋理解八十六條咧，係有任何嘅改革性，對於改善陪審團制度咧，係唔應該會違反基本法八十六條嘅嗱。咁第二咧就係誒頭先咧，其實誒Mr誒Blanche Flower係提到咧，佢話即係佢哋都睇到啦，而家好多嘅情況喺處理陪。
審團制度或者係要求嘅時候咧，有任意性啦，有不一致性啦。誒，有好多咧，大家都認為咧，未必係咁好嘅一啲嘅誒誒實踐上嘅一啲問題。但係本身陪審團制度咧，我自己就睇過幾年前咧，城市大學有一個博士論文咧，係專。
專門寫世界各地嘅陪審團制度，連日本嘅陪審團制度嘅利弊，同埋人哋咧有啲已經係研究到咧點樣係cyber jury，即係話咧係因為我哋嘅陪審團制度都會有好多侷限性嘅。你知咧，我哋睇電視啊噉樣咧，戲劇混住喺～
間房係嘛？誒，但係咧，佢哋不斷去研究咧，點樣令到咧，佢真係可以發揮當日。其實陪審團呢樣嘢係有一個歷史嘅。事實上咧，亦都有其他嘅管轄區嘅司法機關咧，係嚟過香港咧，係想參考香港嘅陪審團制度。嗱，咁所以咧，我哋覺得。
香港嗰個陪審團制度咧，應該係精益求精，同埋咧係誒下一次我哋有機會再翻嚟呢個委員會咧。其實我都係啊，覺得我哋可以邀請更多專門研究陪審團制度，特別喺普通法制度裏面，佢哋咧係點樣係發揮到咧？係陪審團制度嗰個利弊，譬如香港嘅。
陪審團制度咧，其實我哋都進行過改革啦，因為我哋有知識上啊、語言上有好多嘅要求，亦都限制咗某一類人咧，佢有機會參加呢個陪審團嘅制度嘅。咁所以我都想有少少嘅評價咧，我覺得楊專員可能稍為咧喺呢一方面咧係保守咗一啲。噉我覺得可以開放。
啲咧去睇下咧，大家喺呢一方面，世界各地。
嘅研究，因為亦都有佢嘅弊處嘅，的確有案件出現咗咧，可能係因為有陪審團嘅嘅誒嗰個判斷，未必大家覺得係特別公道，但係佢亦都發揮咗好耐嘅歷史嘅價值。咁所以呢一方面咧，我都希望我哋係會再一次有機會，仲會係邀請更多喺呢方。
方面可能係有研究嘅誒一啲誒朋友啦，佢哋嚟呢一度咧，我哋喺委員會嗰度進行討論。咁而家咧就誒，我諗係阿石禮謙議員係好想發言。唔係，我想問，即係我我想求證啊，阿朱議員頭先解釋誒，我都聽到好詳細，佢佢用。
八十喺八十六嗰條，佢解釋係咪用係用第八條去解釋到八十六嗰度咧？阿專業。
對唔住，係嗱，不如咁噉，我都解釋下。本來我哋就劃咗線啦。咁不過咧，呢個議題咧，由頭先我哋都休會咗十分鐘。噉我亦都有誒權限咧，可以係誒增加十五分鐘喺個會議。咁石禮謙議員係誒好有興趣問咧，我哋就誒畀四分鐘你。
唔使四分鐘。張生佢點解去解釋嗰陣時，係我想了解個第八條同埋八十六條去嗰頭先去解釋嗰度係咪喺呢一方面去解咁？不如阿楊專員你就一並總結啦。佢唔使四分鐘，你總結曬同埋回應曬我哋嘅問題，好冇？首先，關於基本法第八十六條咧，我頭先係誒回答阿謝議員嘅提問嘅時。
時候咧提到呢一個第八十六條嘅其中一個可能嘅睇法，其實我嘅根據咧就係誒喺原審嘅時候，誒就係喺誒誒呢啲Jagdan case原審嘅時候，原審法官咧係曾經就住呢一方面係誒。
做過一啲嘅講過一啲睇法嘅，其實當時佢睇法就係噉。
佢提完第佢重重申咗《第基本法》第八十六條之後咧，佢喺判詞係十六段咁講。
The article is clear and ambiguous. All that is saying is that whatever principle applied in relation to jury trials prior to the basic law coming into effect would continue to apply thereafter.
The applicants cannot be in any better position now than they would have been prior to the basic law coming into effect. They will be in the same position.
What was the principle which was previously practised？跟住佢問完呢個問題之後咧，就引用咗一啲判例，跟住就答，最喺第十九段就係話，consequently，the principle of trial by jury that applied prior to the basic law coming into effect was clear，and indictable
該 offence was triable either by judge and jury in the High Court, or by trial or by judge alone in the District Court at the discretion of the Attorney General. The order of the magistrate transferring the trial to the District Court is one which is not subject to appeal.
The attorney general's discretion was, and hence the respondent's discretion is unfettered, although not necessarily entirely free of judicial supervision.其實就係基於呢幾段咧，我提出呢個係一種睇法，就係基於基本法第十六條所原有嗰兩個字咧，係只係係講緊基本法。
係頒布之前原有嘅制度、原有嘅陪審團原則不變。誒，我都會盡量以一個。
公開啲或者open啲嘅睇法去善釋基本法第八十六條，正如頭先我上次答阿謝議員嘅提問嘅時候，就住呢方面咧，誒，我哋呢個當然正如頭先講係一種睇法，但係究竟一個真正嘅法律觀點係點樣咧？
若果我哋下次翻嚟嘅時候咧，我都希望喺呢方面會做多啲誒比較。誒誒，就住整體上頭先啊，Mr. Mr. Branch Flower所講話，佢對於
呢個第啊，我哋嘅檢控守則第八點四條嘅有一啲嘅誒唔滿意。其實啊，Mr. Branch Flower同我喺今年年頭咧，其實已經就住呢個議題，大家坐低而都傾過，亦都有一啲書信嘅往來。咁亦都好明白佢同埋大律師公會就住呢一方面嘅。
嘅嘅睇法，但係誒，我哋都可以噉樣睇。第一，就住話需唔需要喺檢控守則裏邊提翻就住。
普通法原則之下，選擇陪審團審訊制度呢一方面嘅好壞，我頭先已經喺呢方面嘗試解答。但係就住話誒，被告人可唔可以就住呢一方面作出陳詞？誒，我亦都同大律師公會誒幾次溝通，亦都講過就係。
係，其實喺唔同嘅審訊階段，喺唔同嘅範疇裏邊咧，誒現代嘅辯方律師咧。
都會喺唔同嘅情況之下去將陳喺嘅陳用陳詞方式將佢哋嘅觀點講畀控方聽。其實就住呢一方面咧，啊控方係絕對唔會唔考慮。啊，其實啊話係咪話一定重？唔我哋唔寫出嚟喺個喺個守則度唔寫出嚟就係唔重要咧？呢？
方面，我覺得好大保留嘅。
誒就住話誒，現在嘅守則所列出所羅列出嘅九點，大部分都係以前翻炒嘅，其實呢點亦都唔係好公平。就住現在新嘅九點咧，有五點係一啲重要觀點喺舊嘅檢控守則裏邊有，但係有四點咧係全新嘅，其中。
有兩點咧係特別重要嘅，嗰兩點咧其實就係相應當時喺草擬呢一個檢控守則嘅時候，聽過大律師公會同埋律師公律師會嘅誒陳詞之後咧，我理解刑事檢控科係專登加特意加落去嘅。嗰兩點係邊兩點咧？其中一點。
就係第一。
F嗰點，被告是否在社會上有地位、身負重任或處於受信崗位？呢個第一。第二，頭先啊啊，Mr. Brandflower講，現在檢控守則冇特意提話，當去到一啲啊dishonest嘅案件裏邊咧，就應該要係喺陪審團或者高院審噉。但係其實G呢一點咧。
亦都講得頗清楚，就係需與裁定的事實事宜是否涉及社會的標準及價值觀。其實就住話係咪不誠實呢個，正正就係涉及社會嘅價值觀。所以呢度有一個觀點係特別係就住嗰一個誒觀點嚟回應嘅。咁頭。
頭先啊啊，Mr. Blanchflower亦都講話係咪有一啲情況，譬如話牽涉到誒professional專業人士，就更加應該因為佢哋個誒專業。
係，又係咪係咪因為呢啲呢類人人士佢哋嘅特特殊身份，就應該係喺高院審咧？咁嗱，我哋我亦都詳細考慮過呢一點。咁若果，
誒專業人士有權做一啲嘢，噉係咪唔係專業人士就冇權做咧？呢一個其實我就覺得唔，我自己都唔係好過到我自己呢一關。
誒，但係整體上誒，主席就住各方面嘅議題誒。當然，若果誒委員會係誒會喺遲啲重新就住某一啲特定嘅議題係誒再討論嘅話咧，我會樂意協助。好誒，今日咧就。
我哋都誒，真係時間到咗啦。噉我都好相信咧，我哋係一定會將呢個議題咧再擺喺待議事項。咁亦都咧，即係我因為聽到楊專員嘅誒回應啦，因為咧所謂嘅原有制度不變咧，其實基本法仲有其他條文都係噉嘅資本主義制度。咁如果你話樣樣，
都唔變咧，噉就真係我哋就改革上咧就根本冇曬空間。我相信咧一定係有空間去改進嘅。咁咧就誒，我好多謝誒大陸師公會嘅代表Mister.Plant Flower同埋咧我哋嘅誒律政處嘅代表。咁今日咧我哋時間亦都到啦，我哋係相信咧亦都會機有機。
機會咧，再就呢個問題進行探討嘅。多謝大家。咁今日會議結束，係一句好短啊。頭先大陸施工會嘅代表話，可能遲啲佢哋可以做一份更加詳盡嘅意見書畀我哋呢個委員會考慮。噉我希望誒大陸施工會如果係能夠嘅話咧，就係喺我哋下一次再討論之前咧，就早少少畀嗰個。
意見書，我哋咁能令到我哋可以更加全面噉樣去檢討成件事。係，我呢個咧，我哋都會係啊誒會咁做，同埋我哋都睇下邊一方，即係有一啲人佢喺呢方面其實做咗一啲好好嘅研究咧，可能你呢一度表達佢嘅意見，亦都係對我哋係好有參考嘅價值嘅。咁多謝大家，下會議結束。