官員啊，同埋誒人士出席啊，各位同事而家夠鍾而家夠法定人數啊，張超洪議員已經寫咗信嚟，係退出呢個會議。
噉就誒今日嘅誒項目咧，就係三跑道系統設嘅嘅計劃同埋工程範圍同埋造價，係包括填海工程同埋成本嘅控制嘅。
O.K.歡迎誒政府官員同埋機管局嘅同事係誒誒出席今日嘅會議嘅。啊，或者我首先畀誒副局長去講講誒。
誒依個誒三跑嘅。
啊！事先啊，然後至係畀阿阿林總裁嘅啊，局長。
誒主席誒，多謝你畀少少時間我做一個簡單嘅開場啦。今日咧就係請咗誒機管局嘅行政總裁同佢嘅誒同事咧，係誒向各位委員咧係介紹香港國際機場策劃中嘅三跑道系統嘅工程。
項目嘅範圍同埋佢個費用嘅詳細嘅情況㗎，咁誒詳細情況當然啦，文件誒亦都係發咗畀大家，大家可以參考。誒文件之中亦都提到咧，喺運輸及房屋局核下嘅機場工程統籌辦公室，為咗要去監察有關嘅工程嘅進行咧，亦都係。
會係建議咧，係聘請顧問提供呢個監察同核證嘅服務㗎。呢個亦都請誒委員會咧，係都係係備悉㗎。而家我想請咧林天福先生咧，係介紹有關於三跑嘅工程內容。好啊，誒基建局總裁阿林生。
誒，多謝，多謝主席。
我哋誒整個三跑誒工程嘅嗰個設設計啦，同埋嗰個誒預算啦等等咧，係都係過去嗰誒兩三年咧，就經過誒好多唔同嘅即係專家核實。咁依家咧，我就想請誒我哋誒有關工程負責嘅總。
甲阿潘先生向大家咧就介紹整個工程嘅嗰個誒誒範圍啦，同埋嗰個費用等等問題。好啊，阿潘生。
Thank you, Chairman. Good morning. It's my delight to take you through this morning the scope of the project and covering cost and also the management process that we will be using.
I'm sure you're all very familiar with the airport site itself. Are two runways, one point five.
誒同事啊，或者未開啊潘生誒，Mr. Poo嘅嗰個麥，可唔可以幫我開開？
係。
I'm on. Sorry. Okay. Sure. Apologies. I'll go move closer. Members, I'm sure we're very familiar with the airport site itself. We have two runways, north and south, separated by roughly one five kilometres. Between them is our iconic terminal one building. You'll see on the right hand side of the.
And also, also between the runways, you see the I concourse there, which is the midfield concourse, which will be opened very shortly. The capacity of the airport is reaching such that we need another runway. But the project is, of course, very much more than just a runway.
We have to reclaim further land of some 650 hectares. On that land, we will be building a second, a third parallel runway, which will become the new north runway. The existing north runway will become a new central runway. We have taxiways connected.
Between the two runways, we have a third runway concourse, the building which will be where we get on and off the planes, of course, and where we wait for those planes. That will be the crucial element for customer treatment.
Also, in red there on purple on the right of Terminal One, adjacent Terminal One, we have to expand Terminal Two into a full processing terminal that will serve that third runway concourse, and it will be connected via an APM system and a baggage handling system to the third runway concourse.
係。
我哋想帶你過每一個元素，只係多咗少少細節。
嗯。
The reclamation, to form 650 hectares of reclamation, we've taken the view that we're not going to, for environmental reasons, we are not going to be dredging. So this reclamation will all be done on top of the existing marine muds that exist there.
We've carried out extensive site investigations, such that we know the depth and the type of muds we've got there. We have an added complication in in the area that we also have the footprint. About 40% of the footprint overlies the existing contaminated mud pits, which were established at the beginning of the 90s, not connected with the airport, but
They have materials in them that are potentially hazardous to the environment. So, our reclamation is basically there's three main elements to form that land. What we have to do is first of all ground improvement to the to the muds that that will underlie the the land. We have to.
Build seawall right the way around the outside, some 13 kilometres of seawall, and then the filling operation in two main elements: both marina environment, and then once we get above the sea level, there's a significant land-based fill material.
The fill material largely be done by sand, but once we get above ground, we'll be also using public fill where we can.
Just a bit more on the different colours on that diagram. There, we show the different types of ground treatment that are necessary in areas where there's the contaminated mud pits. The area shown pink, we have to, we will be carrying out a technique called deep cement mixing. This is where we mix cement with the marine mud and thereby solidify.
and make it a load-bearing platform that can take the load of the reclamation. In areas outside that, we'll be using a number of methods, including prefabricated vertical drains, the PVD, whereby you encourage the marine muds to settle, to sink quickly, and to do
This you have to allow the water to come out of the within the muds.
And for the seawall, there'll be a variety of construction techniques using both DCM and also stone columns to provide a very stable foundation to those seawalls.
What's formed on that land, we will then be providing taxiway and runways. As I've already mentioned, the new runway will be parallel, some more than one and a half kilometres apart from the the current north runway. It will have dual taxiways to the south of it, and also on that diagram you'll see we're providing dual taxiways to the north.
of what will now be the centre runway.
There's a number of works we need to do to the existing runway. So there's a period where we actually have to open the new runway and close the old north runway, the centre runway, to reconstruct that. We have to put tunnels underneath the runway, but also we need to materially change it so that it can work and efficient, and also build rapidly.
Around taxiways around each end of the runway to allow the maximum effective use of that runway in the future.
The runway and taxiway systems all be designed to international ICAO standards. These are the standards that govern all airfield design.
So between the two, the new runway and the centre runway, will be the third runway concourse. This is a large concourse building, some 283,000 square metres. It will have, with its aprons and the contact stands, some 57 positions. 34 of those will be contact stands where you get on and off the aircraft.
直入到建築。
As you can see, there code F, code E, it will be catering with a maximum flexibility to allow different size of aircraft with the forecast mix that we anticipate, and it will be able to accommodate right up to the the very largest aircraft, the code F, which is the A380.
Obviously, it's very much got to be customer focused in terms of ease of use, and so we've used as a base our iconic Terminal One building, which is very successful. But learning from the very experience we've had in operating this, we believe this concourse will be even better. It has the same aesthetic.
As perhaps as T1, although not a copy, the intention is to get much light into it to make it a very nice, pleasant ambient space for people to use to really drive customer experience for the for the travelling passengers.
And there'll be a number of innovative features in the building that we hope will make it a very, very green building indeed.
This is another view, although titled commercial node. This is the the node of the Y shape of the terminal concourse. It's although obviously it will be a feature of it to have commercial and and F and B facilities there. The reason also to show it is it will this will be where you arrive having.
Come off the APM into the third runway concourse as a departing passenger, and again you'll see the intention is to make the building intuitively wayfinding, such that you can easily find your way around the building in the same manner that that you do in the the current terminal one.
作為我所提到的，航廈是顯然在跑道之間，但處理航站樓將會遠離它，鄰近航站樓一號，這意味著我們必須做出決定，擴大現有的航站樓二號。航站樓二號是在幾年前建造的，在。
The third runway was envisaged and is really only a fairly modest departure-only facility and relying back onto terminal one for its concourse. So the terminal two, the expanded terminal two, will be very much a much bigger building. You can see the dotted red line is the the envelope of the current.
T2， and the intention is to to expand that building and at the same time retain as much of that building as we can， to enable but but always realising that we want to make this as the most efficient processing terminal we can. So it will very much mirror the experience that we have today in Terminal One in terms of efficiency.
There you can see in blue. You can see the size of the building. It's more than twice the size in terms of floor plate area, in terms of total square metres. We also have two buildings, north annex and south building, adjacent to it. These will provide many of the facilities necessary, such as car parks, pick up, limousine lounge.
car parking for for the for the whole airport and facility. The terminal two, as I say, is going to be a full processing terminal. So unlike the terminal today, it will have a full arrivals level. It will also have the meets and greeters, the the baggage carousels, all of the facilities.
That have to be added to make it a full processing terminal.
In addition to that, we also need to greatly expand the APM system to connect seamlessly between T1 and also the new third runway concourse from T2. So underground, we will also be building what we call the airport interchange station. This is an APM train interchange underneath the building, which will allow us to connect to the existing.
T一線，and also provide a very efficient APM service out to the the new concourse. We also have to build a depot there, and as you can see, a large part of the facility is a baggage handling basement. This is obviously a very major baggage handling system has to be provided for the new expanded facility, and of course the existing T二 doesn't have that.
And we're careful to add that basement. Although it is a basement, it's not going to be beneath the existing terminal two.
所以那APM系統，那會連接至第三跑道航廈，你見到喺圖形上邊。站距約2.6公里，而列車的頭尾時間，四卡列車最初會係約2.5分鐘，類似地，實際旅程時間會係略過2.5分鐘。
That's very similar to the journey time from currently you'll see on in T1 the APM system runs you're familiar I'm sure with Eastall to Westall E H and W H and at the end of this year that system will be extended out to the Midfield Concourse. A very similar journey time for someone in T1 going out to the Midfield Concourse will be similar to the journey from.
T2 to the third runway concourse. We are not bound by the existing train system, so the advantage is that we'll be able to use faster trains and slightly larger trains to provide that service. There's also because it's a must-ride system, we've got a high, we need a high level of redundancy on the system. So in the existing system in T1
一 runs on what we call a pinch loop, where the train goes one way and then turns and goes back the other way.
We will do the same system on the original on the TRC line, but we will provide a third running tunnel that can allow us. If there's a problem in one, we can immediately switch to enable that. That high level of redundancy is necessary for the train to continue running from TRC to T two. And in the future, we're even protecting for a.
Further forth, in the event that there's a decision to expand the third runway concourse at some point in the future.
The other key element, of course, in terms of apart from getting passengers there, we need to get their baggage. So the baggage handling system will use the latest technology, an individual carrier system. This is an ICS system. This is different from the existing system we have in T1, which is very close underneath the processing terminal. This one has to travel a distance, so it's.
It's a very different philosophy. It travels five times faster than our baggage system, and will able enable us to to still deliver the bags to meet the the current KPIs that we enjoy with T1. Even though the extended distance, it will also allow us to a very efficient system for delivering bags for arriving planes than.
And different from the T1 system we enjoy today.
嗯。
So on the layout of the reclamation, you'll see there's two blue areas east and west of the main facilities. These are much needed aviation support facilities. The eastern support area and the western support area. Characteristically, the eastern support area is a mixture of air.
Side facilities, ground support equipment and the like, but also landside facilities that will have a police station, fire station and other facilities. The western support area is more predominantly aviation support. It will have facilities for maintenance, aircraft maintenance, as well as another fire station for the.
The new third runway.
嗯。
Construction cost. I'd like to just take a little bit of time over this slide. I'm sure since March when we presented it, the the figures that we presented for the construction of the third runway concourse is 141.5 million billion dollars in money of the day. This is the familiar number.
This is recognising that the money won't all be spent in one day. It will be spent over a period of eight years of construction. That is the cost of the project, and that is how projects are always presented in terms of money of the day, money of when it will be spent.
Back in the when we did the master plan estimate in two thousand and thirty, we presented two figures. A figure that was current for for one day only in two thousand and ten, and then added the money that turned it into a money a day figure. So those two figures there, you can see, are eighty six point two and one thirty six. The only reason that we we presented again this eighty four point five in the.
Red box there is simply for transparency, so that we can.
所以refer back members to compare with what we said in the master plan to where what's
我們有現在呈現，所以，master plan for the money of the day was one hundred and thirty six point two， and the figure today is one hundred and forty one point two， a slight increase， but but but a very slight increase。 I think you'll agree。
But both of those figures are money of the day. That's the money when it will be spent. So just to focus on that, the breakdown of that money of the day, you won't be surprised to see that land formation and marine works is is the highest single item under that estimate of 56.2.
Very briefly, I can split that into the main constituents. I've said before we have ground improvement, which is a very substantial element, which represents a very significant commitment from the airport authority to treat this ground, to not dredge any material for the reclamation, and to make sure that we trap or and deal with.
the contaminated mud in a very responsible way. The fill management—that's the cost of forming the land, including importing all of the sand and placing the materials—and then there are a number of utility diversions under that. So that all adds up to the 56.2.
The next item is the runway and airfield facilities, 11.5 billion. Again, a breakdown of those figures in terms of runway, taxiway and taxi lanes is 5.2 billion. The airfield support areas, all the infrastructure needed for those, is 1.7. And then there's an airside road network of 4.6. This includes the two tunnels beneath the the current north runway.
未來， centre 運行。
你會見到，然後Apron Works。
Sorry, apron works below that at five billion. This is the work of the actual flat aprons around the third runway concourse.
The terminal two modification works, I'll break that down. The 16.5 money of the billion bunny of the day, we are retaining much of terminal two, all of the foundations, all of the substructures, the APM basement structure as well. But we are significantly expanding the building, so there there will be a much bigger footbrake plate.
And there are significant basements associated with the baggage handling and the new APM system. So those come to five seven billion. The architectural works and works of the fit out of the terminal two, the much larger building, is four two, and ENM services and systems is six six. I would also add that with terminal two, we will be retaining many of the ENM systems that are in the building.
We will have to increase the size of them, obviously, but many of the chiller plants, etc., will be reused.
The last of the elements I'll break down is the third runway concourse. Again, another very significant item, 26.3 billion dollars. The foundation structures and the the main structure of the building is some 12 billion dollars. The architectural fitout works 4.5, and the APM system works 6.5.
這些都consistent with the numbers in the back of the paper. So other than that, we have the APM system of 10.10.9 billion dollars. That is obviously again another significant commitment, but it is a must ride system, and so there's a significant level of redundancy in that system to make sure that it is always working.
A baggage handling system again, it has to travel a fair distance and also be extremely robust and reliable. And then the further item is the airport support facilities and utilities. These are the general civil works associated with the the main building.
所以那係總成本的拆解，係一四一.點五。
Just to close, just to cover on in terms of our own experience. Since airport opening, the airport authority has invested some thirty billion dollars in capital expenditure, and over twenty billion of that in large projects that have been run by its own in-house management professionals.
ixture of engineers, architects and systems specialists, all with a knowledge of the airport, many of whom worked on the original airport construction. And so they they acutely aware they understand the challenges of constructing an airport operating environment. And of course, we have established project management processes and procedures that were based on the original airport construction and have.
被 hone in the years since.
嗯。
In looking at the management structure, we have a variety of management processes, either which can be loosely looked at in terms of a hierarchical type system or a matrix type project management system. The hierarchical system is very good for certain projects.
But it does mean that some data, common data such as cost and programme, are filtered up through the various levels of the organisation. For that reason, we're proposing to use a matrix system whereby certain functional procedures such as cost, programme and quality are taken aside and have separate function.
heads within a project management office, and then the project delivery team are focusing on the actual construction management. This simplifies the reporting on certain critical items such as cost and programme, and make sure that there's clear transparency at the top as to where any at any one point. This is particularly
relevant to a project that has many different types of construction, civil building systems, and so it really does lend itself to the various different project management packages that will be there. So this is the project management structure for the airport authority. As you can see there on the left, the project delivery team, their focus is to to manage the
Construction and delivery with the contractor. The project management office contains certain functional key leaders, who have staff matrixed into the project delivery team, but who report to them on certain functions such as cost, budget, quality, safety and environment.
to ensure compliance across all of the projects consistently.
嗯。
Also within the airport authority, we have a very healthy oversight structure. This is the structure for the third runway already in operation. Although its basis of having a committee within the board that looks at construction is long established. So within the management team, the CEO has a management coordination meeting on a
very regular basis with the EDS and and also the project team looking at progress and and monitoring the project itself. Additionally, there's a steering group chaired by our chairman, again that involves all of the executive directors to ensure the proper reporting and and transparency of the process of the of the project. And again, beneath
The board we have a committee, the 3Rs and Works Committee, long established as the Works Committee. It now also functions to manage and review the progress and costs associated with the third runway. In addition, of course, we have a committee on Audit, Committee and Finance, which has a separate role under our board structure.
structure, and of course, I would add at the working level, we enjoy a very good relationship in terms of coordination with the airport expansion coordination office. We allow to we constantly liaise with them and report to them on progress and matters that related to the project.
Just a few slides to finish, Chairman. Thank you. Obviously, we are now in the detailed design stage, and we've started that. But this comes at the end of a long process whereby we've been planning for this since master plan. Since that period, we've done a number of advanced elements, including those we've taken a very comprehensive site investigation.
of the area, the area where the reclamation will be is unconstrained in terms of our access to it. We've done a lot of marine site investigation, and that diagram just shows you some of it. The in terms of making sure that we fully understand the the material that we will be forming the land over.
equally we have very detailed records of the actual land that formed the Chhatrapati Airport and and so equally the terminal two expansion has has access to all of that data.
嗯。
Also, things that we've been doing in the last year and coming to a head is obviously we've developed a Project Master programme. That was part of a three elements in terms of a very comprehensive exercise assisted by international consultants to look at the procurement strategy and risk assessment, along with the Project Master programme. So they're all integrated.
That risk assessment is just the first start of a risk assessment. We now have turned that into a risk management plan, and that is something that's a dynamic tool that will go forward in the project where we monitor risks that were identified. Now we add to them, but more importantly, we use it to avoid risks. And if there are risks are coming up that we can use mitigate and have contingent actions in.
the event that they occur.
The project budget estimate I've already talked through was prepared by an independent consultant, reviewed by our own my own team, but also also was vetted by the government-appointed M and V consultant, and the project budget includes an appropriate level of contingency.
所以我們進入設計階段。 at the moment， we're lucky that we had a scheme design in parallel with the IA process， which finished last year. In parallel with that， we means by doing a scheme design， we've got a very very detailed scope of what the project is， and so it's fully developed exactly what the scope of the project is. We have peer review and design construction.
By independent experts at appropriate times, we have a very experienced client which we use to also interrogate the designers, make sure that the design is delivering genuine operational need, and of course that leads towards a cost effectiveness of the facilities that we're planning.
The design process is a constant process of designing. We look at value engineering all the time, and we're particularly key to make sure that the project is fit for purpose, but also value for money, and avoids any extravagant or unnecessary features.
Design freeze is something that will happen during the project as the project is completed. When we get to a detailed design stage, we sign off that process and thereby try and avoid any creeping design changes as once we start construction, and thereby avoid the risk of cost escalation during construction.
Thank you very much, chairman. Members.
誒，局長有冇嘢補充添？
好啊，噉就而家有。
九位誒同事問嘅誒十位同事啊啊啊副主席誒十一位，噉就誒。
一人四分鐘先好嘛？啊，我讀讀個名：郭嘉琪、啊啊梁繼昌、李卓仁、啊。
陳偉業、阿盧偉國、阿謝偉全、阿姚思榮、單仲佳、阿胡志偉同埋阿。
副主席。
阿阿何俊仁，好嘛？噉就郭嘉琪。
多謝主席。啊，四分鐘。好啊。
就都多謝機管局啲誒同事嚟咗。不過咧，所有呢啲噉嘅重複講話個工程係點樣可以誒包到成本咧？其實喺呢個立法會嗰度聽過唔唔知幾多次。
頭先咧，啱啱我哋喺公務小組就嗰個港珠澳大橋就超支咗。
百分之十五。
尋日爆出嚟嘅高鐵就超支百分之三十，蓮塘口岸唔夠兩年超支百分之五十。
根本呢個一千四百一十五億嘅工程咧，大家睇到機管局由最初到而家只係。
係畀咗係三。
百億嘅錢，但係而家一條三跑道咧，就已經差唔多機管局幾倍咁耐嘅投入嘅資金。
空場空域嘅問題，到而家咧，政府都係。
得把口嘅啫，叫一紙嘅文件冇。
所有嗰啲估計咧。
真係唔知點樣去信佢。譬如頭先我係講港珠澳大橋，以前嘅估計嘅流量咧，最高係每日十六萬架次。
而家香港每日係四萬幾架次，係政府估計嘅四分之一嘅啫。
噉啊，梗係冇所謂啦，因為唔係你哋嘅錢嚟嘅。
基管嗰個總裁又好，啲高官又好，都唔係總裁，誒都唔係你哋嘅錢。
但係，對於嗰啲承建商，梗係肥豬肉啦，一千四百一十五億。
如果以往嘅超支，譬如舉個例啦，超支百分之三十就一千八百四十億，去到蓮塘嗰個水平就二千一百二十二億。
邊一樣嘢我哋信得過你？
你頭先講嗰啲點樣令個工程係去做起？
嗰啲保障個價格咧，其實呃我哋納税人啊市民呃咗好多次嘅。
即係如果難聽啲，佢啲高官係喺任何商業機構已經炒咗啦。
嗰啲錯誤嘅估計。
係咁離譜嘅，三個冇用嗰啲大白象工程。
總共未買單啊！而家估計最少一千六百九啊四億，連同高鐵同埋港珠澳過份高股嘅用量。
我想問局長或者副局長喺而家呢個情況下，你都識講啦。人手又唔夠，物料又唔夠，點解仲要同埋仲有好多嘅法定嘅程序都未做好？空域協議有冇政府點解仲要繞過立法會，夾硬希望出年？
就要簽呢個合約。
你要知道，你簽咗個合約係冇得翻轉頭嘅，嗰啲承建商就一路可以告你㗎啦。
因為你逼佢哋去做啊嘛，機管局話你逼佢做啊嘛，好似而家高誒港鐵噉樣，佢唔使負責任㗎。
港鐵封個頂啦！
咁基管局嗰嗰陣時，到時都話唔關我事嘅，政府叫我去做計錯數嘅，我唔負責。即係主席，我覺得政府如果夾硬要嚟嘅話咧，係不負責任。除咗要佢答之外，我今日有個動議咧，係要求政府。
喺而家人手又解決唔到物料解決唔到，所有啲工程全部係爛尾嘅，係冇法子有一個確切嘅員工人力日期入邊去揀去做咧，只會令我哋納税人香港嘅市民咧。
係繼續將啲錢倒落鹹水海，主席畀佢答。局長，你有卅廿秒秒答。誒，主席啊，好快啫！我哋誒睇到呢個國際機場咧，香港國際機場係好重要嘅，因為點解咧？我哋未來一兩年咧，我哋嗰個嘅機場嗰個處理量咧已經係誒飽和㗎啦，咁所以。
如果我哋唔盡快去做咧，而呢個所謂快咧，機場佢哋而家打算呢個工程都要係用緊啊八年嘅時間嘅。咁八年嘅時間，我哋香港本身當然嗰個嘅市場啊、勞工環境啊，我哋喺未計預計裏邊咧，都會有一啲嘅變化，即係唔係唔係好似我哋今日而家呢個建築高峯期嘅情況噉。
所以我哋覺得係應該睇咗佢需要要去啊上馬嘅嚇。哇，梁繼昌議員。
啊，主席，誒喺個工程項目入邊咧，嗰個填海工程當然係最大宗，同埋你哋要填嘅係六百五十公頃嘅土地。咁最近我睇到港珠澳大橋填海工程嘅技術上出咗好嚴重嘅問題，根本就可能即係連條橋都起唔到。咁而家你而家用呢一個嘅誒中間，我睇到頭先啊。
啊！潘生個頭，攝影片嗰度粉紅色嗰度咧，因為係誒嗰個地方係儲存緊大量嘅污染物啦，需要用一個誒non dredging嘅嘅嘅填海方法，即係一個深層水泥拌合法。噉我想知道咧喺技術上咧，呢個叫深層水泥拌合法有冇一啲失敗？
嘅例子喺喺國際上，我知呢個方填海方法咧係首次喺香港用嘅嚇。如果你你你保障唔到呢一個嘅填海方法係行得通嘅時候咧，嗰個污染程度係非常之之驚人嘅。填海由填海引起污染。噉，另外我仲想問一個問題咧，係關於頭先頭攝影片。
上邊嗰個新嘅誒客運大樓咧，係一個單Y嘅大樓。咁其實嗰度我睇到亦都有一片嘅空地咧，其實夠位喺個雙Y係咪？因為要壓縮你哋嘅開支咧，就唔將嗰個誒客運大樓建雙Y而建做單Y，其實冇乜意思。如果你要做，
就而家做咗佢噉，但係你而家諗住係即係整息整曬啲數嗰度，要要壓縮佢嘅時候，噉係冇意思啊。兩個問題唔該好啊，誒，局長啊，我請誒基本嗰個同事係回答呢個誒兩個問題，或者我先答第二個問題，咁跟住我就請阿潘生誒答有關嗰個。
深層税例法嘅嗰個問題，誒，我哋誒今次咧提出呢個單Y設計咧，其實誒，我哋係因為過去嗰兩年做咗個方案設計之後咧，我哋覺得我哋當日咧就喺嗰個master plan二零三零提出話，希望擴建咗之後能夠再誒再處理多三千萬。
旅客依個情況咧，其實單位已經足夠可以做得到。咁所以喺噉嘅情況之下，我哋覺得冇需要提前咧，就將最後另外嗰一個誒工程都做。咁當然依家我哋預留嘅地方咧，其實喺令到我哋將來有需要嘅情況之下咧，仲可以起埋另外一半誒，能夠將我哋嘅嗰個處理誒旅客嘅嘅。
嗰個誒量咧增加多兩千萬，咁但係我哋覺得如果你太早去起嘅話，當然就即係起完之後就誒你用唔到啦。另外我亦都覺得咧，十幾年後可能響無論係旅客嘅嗰個需要啊，技術上都可能有啲改變。所以如果係將依個即係誒第二期嘅。
工程留待將來先去決定咧，就更加係誒合適嘅。噉我想請潘生解解第一個問題。啊，Mr. Pooh。
Thank you. On DCM, you're correct. It hasn't been used in Hong Kong before. It has been used very widely in Asia and Europe and also the America. It is an established technique. In fact, because it hasn't been used in Hong Kong before, we actually have done a number of trials. The first trial was done a few years ago where we brought a Japanese.
particular rig in to make sure it can be done in Hong Kong conditions, but also looking to make sure it's environmentally acceptable. And we did a lot of monitoring to make sure that it achieves that. In the last year, we've done a further trial which has been comprised of three elements, where we've we've looked at all the techniques that available, basically European.
technique a Japanese technique and a Korean technique, and we've done those trials to to ensure that and to get good engineering data from those processes. In terms of the the scope around the world, they've been used for very many many years. There are 68 major DCM works that have been conducted in Asia in that time in the last 10 years, and
Many of them have been conducted from marine marine environment. I myself have visited both Korea and
Japan with my team to look at live projects going on there. In fact, they've recently in Korea they've been doing a number of significant projects.李卓然議員。
呢隻即係所謂一朝被蛇咬，十年怕草繩。
但係咧，即係呢個政府咬極都唔怕，嗰度好嘢，因為啲錢唔係去嘅嚇。咁但係即係根本成大家睇到最近啲超支真係得人驚嚇。啱講緊高鐵嚇用財技，港鐵無端端冇咗二百億啊，噉啊變咗咧就即係成件成個。
高鐵超支二百幾億咧，根本最後都係納税人錢。你無論港鐵或好，政府又好，根本一樣嘅啫嘛。
噉你機機機管局係政府全資擁有，其實成單嘢已經係冇咗個派息㗎啦，已經五百幾億，政根本納税人已經蝕緊錢落去。咁到時咧，如果又係超支嘅話咧，真係冇眼睇。尤其今次係講緊一千四百幾億。
噉我唔知，即係機管局對個超支個估計係點樣樣嚇。
不過，你估計完咗之後，你勢能劈完都冇用㗎。到時又唔係你畀錢嘅，又係納税人，又係即係政府畀錢，或者係乘客畀錢。
咁所以係可以好不負責任嘅，你哋。
所以我係好擔心四一千四百幾億。
而後期咧，當我睇翻下一個報告咧。
就係即係，我唔知你哋睇完依份報告之後咧，到底你哋做咗啲咩嘢？
就係誒匯豐銀行整咗一個嘅係誒risk assessment，即係誒。
financial adviser final report，即係或者佢哋財務評估嘅一個報告，噉佢係提出咧就五大。
嘅風險位。
噉我用英文講啦，high level design，land reclamation，EIA approval，preliminary quote，risk。
咁五大風險位之後咧，噉佢嘅結論咧就係話，噉我唔知你哋點採納呢個結論啦。就匯豐銀行咧就建議一個所謂。
CAPEX stress即係CAPEX，即係個capital expenditure啦，即係資本投資嘅風險評誒嘅測試之後咧，就係覺得係會高過嗰個基本嘅假設咧係兩成嘅。噉我唔知道你哋點樣睇依一份報告，噉就變咗到使你一千四百幾億本身。
有冇考慮曬呢啲噉嘅風險位？尤其其中咧五百幾億咧係五百六啊幾億咧係攞嚟做呢個填海啦。大家知道咁填海咧就兩幾樣嘢嘅啫。尤其嗰個物料係好緊要，機器係好緊要。咁若全世界都用緊嗰種機器嗰陣時，機器又會飆高，全世界都爭個物。
料嘅時候咧，就係你個物料又會個海沙又會飆高。咁到咧而家海海沙本身個價格，你哋又評估成點？會唔會到時你哋起嘅時候咧，個海沙個價格又飆升，個機器嘅票價飆升，然後跟住又同翻我哋講啦啊，對唔住啦，我哋即係又睇到一個即係。
飆升嘅價格，嚇咁到底依啲噉嘅全部依啲好多嘅成本嘅風險，你哋點樣去係面對啊？好嘛，誒誒林總裁。
誒，我哋好明白誒，社會係非常之關注誒大型誒工程可能出現超支嘅情況。誒，我哋董事局誒，我哋誒管理層同樣係非常之關注誒點樣能夠咧就儘量減少誒工程出現超支嘅呢個呢個風險。
誒，我哋一個預算係經過誒幾重嘅獨立嘅一啲顧問咧，就嚟誒確定。噉我哋都係有信心呢一個一個合理嘅一個預算。誒，當然我哋需要做嘅就係前期要做好誒各種嘅一啲風險管理。誒，響整個工程進行期間。
嘅個嗰個誒項目嘅管理要要做好誒咁誒，我哋依家誒其實依段時間做嘅就係點樣能夠將呢個風險盡量減到最低。陳偉業議員，啊，主席。
啊！你冇你你你冇畀時間佢答，冇辦法。陳輝怡，邊個？我主席即係我唔期望即係誒政府或者交通局有咩問題答啦。但係我想攞幾份報告，即係唔知可唔可以公開？因為當年興建赤鱲角嘅時候咧，呢啲報告咧係全部公開嘅啊，即係包括呢一個嘅機場嗰個嘅財務研究。
嘅報告啊，即係好詳細嘅。我哋都相信機管局係做咗一份即係好詳細嘅報告。咁同埋亦都有關工程嘅計劃咧，因為其實我瞭解嗰個嘅有關大樓同埋嗰個停泊位係大幅改變嘅。即係早期嗰個計劃咧，二零一零做設計嘅時候咧，嗰陣時應。
應該係有成近八九十個即係停機位嘅，即係最近呢一個係大幅削減咗一半啦。噉我唔知道即係嗰個削減問低。另外就係有關嗰個海沙嘅問題咧，因為我記得當時興建赤鱲角機場嘅時候咧，政府有細計話啲海沙喺邊度嚟㗎，包括西貢啊，包括呢個嘅即係嚟。
嚟到附近啊，咁有曬計劃幾多公公噸啊？挖幾耐有曬噉，家都完全冇資料，係嘛？究竟你填海啲物料嘅來源係點？咁嗰個預計價格好重要嘅。噉我希望有一個即係，如果你呢啲報告畀我哋自己睇咧，就唔使喺度講咁多啦，係嘛？因為即係既然廿幾年前喺港英年代。
殖民地殖民地年代啊，啲報告都公開，我睇唔到。家下啲報告可唔可以公開咯？噉就誒係咯，即係希望同埋嗰個乘客嘅估計啦。即係我知道機管局以前做咗啲研究估計嘅乘客量係幾多噉啊？呢幾年其實有改變嘅啊，同你嘅預計有改變嘅咁呢啲資料都重要㗎嘛。
你起好嗰陣時，其實即係你百年後起好，其實個機場已經即係按你嘅預計，其實已經飽和㗎啦，係嘛？即係你起好啊，要再起啊，已經啊，不如唔好起係嘛？咁所以呢啲資料，我覺得係重要咯。可唔可以公開呢啲資料畀即係畀我哋睇咧？我話誒，總裁。
都誒。
落雨咧，就將。
依家我哋黐。
當然，我哋咧仲接。
當初二零三零報告入邊就講嘅嗰啲就誒向大家提供。不過我想啊，竇靖據我所知，我哋當初二零三零係冇誒係預計係起八十幾。依家我哋起嘅嗰個誒拍飛機嘅位同誒當時二零三零係相若嘅。噉我好樂意喺呢方面咧。嗱，我唔知你哋報嘅。
幾多份啊？可能二零三零之前仲有一份報告㗎嘛，係嘛？我哋冇做過啦。我哋二零三零咧就當時做嘅嗰個所謂二零三零master plan就係為誒三跑準備一個咧，就係得一份。咁如果我哋其實依家，所以點解頭先阿潘總監都將兩個誒預算咧作個比較？實體上，因為我哋。
希望大家都誒知道係當年二零三零嘅時候，我哋提出嘅嗰個方案同埋價格，同依家有啲乜嘢嘅改變？咁當然咧，唔係話完全冇改變，因為點解咧？入邊咧就設計嘅過程入邊，當入邊有啲優化咗啦，有啲嘢我哋覺得，但係基本大嘅嗰啲一啲誒當時嘅預計，同依家冇乜大幅嘅分別。噉我哋好樂意為你哋提供呢方面，同埋啲公。
工程預計係重要嘅，主席特別海沙嗰個成本係好重要嘅，即係即係你喺香港挖同埋喺呢一個嘅，即係唔知去到邊度挖翻嚟嗰個運輸成本。因為當年啲海沙嘅價錢，即係係挖挖嘅成本啫嘛，係嘛就冇嗰個買嘅成本㗎嘛。咁呢呢個係導致到個機場嗰個嘅價格大幅上升嗰期。
好重要嘅理由。噉我哋依家確實咧就預計海砂必須要誒進口，因為香港依家本身咧已經冇誒足夠嘅海砂，噉我哋希望能夠從珠三角進口，所以我哋嘅預算入邊係預計埋係需要採購海砂嘅價格入去。噉你依家預計幾多錢一公噸啊？
我哋。
依家一時我諗又提供唔到啦。咁另外當然亦都要預計到時可能咧就係誒到我哋買嘅時候個價格，我哋預埋個inflation啦。噉我哋但我樂意喺方面提供依方面資料。你遲少少可以用書面提供啦，好嘛？主席幾時可以畀到啲報告我哋睇啊？即係我想可以安排啲時間睇嗰啲。啊，我諗你即係等佢哋翻去睇睇。
然後盡快畀啲報告，好唔該，好嘛？阿盧偉國。
誒，多謝主席。
主席就目前咧，的確有好多大型嘅公務工程咧，去到施工嘅高峯期。咁但係呢個鋪排咧，亦都絕對唔係圓底。誒，嗰個時間上係想噉樣，而係真係各種嘅原因咧，包括係政治上嘅原因啦、司法複核啊，咁令到啲工工。
風情咧就堆積埋一齊，咁但係另一方面咧，就我哋都真係要為誒。
將來嚇香港可持續發展著想咧，亦都真係有啲高基建工程咧，即係一路需要開展。噉啊，而家開展呢個誒機場三跑系統嘅工程咧，其實而家係需要做好多前期嘅工作。咁呢個咧亦都唔會話一下子就去到個嗰個施工高。
風期噉，所以咧呢個即係誒唔需要過太過過濾呢個問題，但係當然我哋要關注。誒，我想問呢個技術性啲嘅問題，因為港珠澳大橋嘅人工島嘅填海咧，係用呢個不進挖嘅方式。
噉我知道存在啲技術上嘅困難，因為海底嘅誒淤泥啦。誒，如果係不盡發挖咧，係企圖係即係一路噉樣係用誒外力去壓實，亦都包括咧大型嘅鋼桶誒嘅誒誒嘅，即係圍住佢啊，或者係。
係呢啲所謂碎石裝嘅噉樣，咁誒都誒真係嗰個客觀個問題咧，就係嗰沉降與壓實啲淤泥咧，係有陣時係唔係話百分之百可以完全係我哋主觀願望控制得咁準確嘅。咁而家三跑系統填海工程咧，係而。
而家建議嘅即係深層水泥拌合咧，同呢個港珠澳大橋人工島嗰個工程技術嘅分別喺邊度？我諗亦都趁咗個機會咧，可以向公眾解釋一下。第二方面咧，就係誒睇到個譬如第三個台影片都睇到㗎啦，其實個工程裏邊咧都好多要好高嘅誒。
設備咧喺海面嘅，咁呢個對於嗰個航道嘅高限啊等等，會唔會帶來嘅工程上一啲影響咧？或者係影響咗嗰個即係施工嘅安排咧？咁？
好啊！誒，啱解釋啲嘛？誒，Mr.蒲。
Thank you. In terms of the construction, as I've said, the pink area there is deep cement mixing. The settlement because we're mixing cement within that area, the ground improvement for that area means that there'll be very little settlement in the actual marine muds itself. We actually turn them into an engineering material. In the other areas.
We will control settlement by conducting, as I say, the process of getting the water out of the mud is the key process. So what we do is we we put in sand drains into that area and then we drain it by by by putting a surcharge of up to ten metres high above that material to settle it much.
The intention of of all the ground improvement is to make sure that all of the the the big settlements, the primary settlements, occur during the construction phase before we start constructing the facilities on the top. So the techniques are all around accelerating that process, such that we have it then have a stable basis on which to then build the the subsequent.
Infrastructure on top.
係有冇跟進啊，羅偉國議員？誒，嗰啲高限嗰啲唔會影響個工程進度係咪？唔好清楚。係，誒，Mr. Paul。
Sorry, yeah, no. The the we we're already taking measures with CAD to make sure that the plant that needs to operate in the area for the DCM and land formation areas can all work within the the height restriction area. You'll see two areas that the yellow at the either end on the right and left extreme that we've got low headroom.
DCM， this is a technique where actually there is plant that actually can operate even under the height restrictions in those areas. So no， it won't be a constraint on the construction.
誒，我話啲話話畀同事聽，我就問完第一輪咧，我就會處理郭嘉琪嘅誒誒動議先，好嘛？噉就然後至畀第二輪發言嘅，噉就誒。
阿謝偉全議員。
多謝主席。誒，當然啦，三炮工程咧，即係一千四百幾億咧，喺史無前例嚇最大嘅工程。大家對呢個工程嚟講咧，吸取咗最近咧，即係好多大型基建工程咧，都超支超時。
噉啊！我想問下運防局咧，即係吸取咗而家我哋高鐵工程嘅嚴重超支同埋滯後咧。
誒政府方面咧，就呢個機場嘅三跑工程咧，佢有咩措施或者安排咧，係防止啊呢個工程又好似高鐵噉嘅情況出現咧？第一個問題，我想啊運防佢答咗先，主席。
主席，嗯，借於謝議員所誒指出誒，用機場管理局去興建三跑系統嘅工程咧，同啊港鐵咧興建高鐵咧係啊嗰個係有相當嘅唔同嘅。啊，我諗喺誒機場管理局方面咧，啊，佢主要係佢用佢。
佢哋本身嘅資金去到誒建造，當然佢亦都用佢自己方法融資去舉債啊，等等啦。但係成個項目本身咧係係建基於佢哋本身嗰個財政嘅狀況去做，所以佢哋本身亦都有一個好大嘅一個嘅誒一個因素咧，係控制好佢嗰個嘅誒成本嘅。
噉啊，控制好本身嗰個工序嘅進行，而我哋本身亦都係設立咗誒，我哋本身嘅誒機場擴建嘅一個嘅統籌嘅辦公室，係去到誒監督佢哋本身嘅。我哋話我監督佢嘅本身嘅工作，亦都係某個程度上咧，亦都係令到佢喺要佢咧。
符合咧本身政府咧其他一啲嘅法定上嘅要求。
誒，我哋亦都係誒聘請我哋本身嗰個嘅誒監察同埋核證嘅一個顧問咧，去到協助我哋個統籌辦公室嘅工作。我相信呢一個係一個誒重要嘅因素咧。呢種嘅關係咧，就係話其實佢哋本身對於點樣樣好好地運用佢哋嘅資金，誒接受市。
場本身嘅誒嘅監督，因為佢哋本身誒亦都係喺舉債嘅時候咧，我相信咧亦都有市場本身嘅力量嘅誒。對於對於誒港鐵本身佢哋嗰個方法誒，其實誒佢哋要亦都係有啊，佢哋本身啊嘅項目監督啦。
誒，佢哋本身遇到嘅問題，我哋覺得喺佢哋處理工程上，高我哋係唔係咁滿意佢嘅做法？誒，我哋誒，所以亦都係有我哋繼續要追究本身喺佢哋要承擔嘅責任。主席誒，即係因為我仲有一個問題嘅，我想嗱呢度咧，可唔可以咧就好簡單，因為機管局咧就。
其實基本上咧，佢就嗰個管理啊、監控咧，都有啲資料畀我哋。政府係冇嘅。咁頭先誒，當然咧就係誒局長有講過，即係話佢哋點做，可唔可以提供呢方面嘅資料咧？呢個第一樣嘢。第二樣嘢咧，我想問下關於嗰個二號嗰個誒誒。
誒擴建嘅，即係嗰個二號誒嗰個客運大樓嘅擴建咧，噉樣。
就誒嗰個數字嚟講咧，即係我想澄清一下咧，就係話佢擴建之後咧三十萬平方米係咪包括呢個南北嘅附屬大樓咧？好啊，安局長就遲啲補翻嚟幾萬。我我哋可以提供翻係嗰個嘅比較啊。嗰個T two個。
個擴建之後嘅數字，或者機管局邊位同事講講？
啊，Mr.蒲。
嗯， yes， I can。 the the three hundred thousand square meters is is the modified of the T two area. The north and south annex building separate from that will be a further hundred thousand square meters。即係主席，即係誒變咗四十萬平方米啦，即係咪咁意思嚇？咁另外我想問一問啊。
啊，時間到啦！或者係姚思榮議員。
誒多謝主席。嗯，我睇到個架構圖咧就好嚴密嚇，分局又好清晰。
噉，但係我哋誒又好擔心，因為誒你分局越清晰咧，誒因為咁大嘅工程一環扣一環咧。如果某一個環節係出咗疑誤咧，會唔會影響到即係成個其他嗰個工序咧，造成一個誒相對噉嘅疑誤？咁誒，我哋希望即係第三條跑道真係能呢個系統。
咧能夠真係喺二零二三年能夠誒真係開放得到。噉我唔知道誒，即係機管局呢方面咧點樣能夠保證咧？即係喺咁分工咁清晰嘅情況之下，能夠嚴密噉樣樣咧，能夠每一個環節都有一個職責喺度。如果呢個職責達唔到，
嘅時候，唔知你哋有冇一個懲處嘅制度咧，使到每一個環節都有個噉嘅責任啦。呢個第一個誒問題。第二問題就個停機位有五啊七個啦。我哋都知道最近好多有啲機咧上嚟喺香港過夜多幾晚咧，機管局都唔同意嘅，因為誒唔足夠停機停機位。
咁將來會唔會即係有呢個問題再發生？即係話要限制一啲機咧，唔可以停得太多晚。咁如果有嘅話，最多可以停到幾多晚咧？有冇呢方面嘅預計？咁始終即係有啲機因為佢係長途嘅，唔可以話即刻飛走嘅。咁呢個情況預計到咩程度咧？噉樣第三個就係嗰個海。
海天碼頭咧就唔知道誒整個工程有冇預算，將來誒有一個咁大嘅需求嘅時候咧，海天碼頭嘅擴建有冇呢方面嘅預算咧？三個問題。好啊，誒，總裁誒，確實好似姚議員講咧，就呢個工程本身係一環扣一環，誒，所以我哋覺得。
最重要就係嗰個信息嘅嗰個溝通係好緊要。就誒，我哋依個誒整個管理系統嘅設計咧，就係希望能夠當如果出現問題嘅時候咧，係係能夠早一啲依啲誒問題咧，就嘅信息咧，就一早能夠咧就係誒去到管理層度能夠及早去解決。
其實工程誒咁複雜，當然你永遠都會出現好多誒問題。誒，我重點不在於會出現問題，重點就係在於能夠提早係誒揾到一啲解決嘅嘅方案。咁所以成個誒，我哋依家管理依個項目嘅設計咧，就希望咧就唔係淨係單一靠由。
誒施工團隊誒畀我哋信息，我哋會有一啲誒人員咧係監督，早啲能夠咧就係誒揾到誒問題嘅嗰個誒根源，同埋提出呢解決嘅一啲誒方法。咁當然咧，如果響呢個過程做得唔好，就表示我哋誒入邊負責嘅嗰啲同事嘅嗰個專業。
表現係喺呢方面係做得唔好啦，噉我但係我係對於我哋嘅團隊係係有信心。咁誒第二個問題咧就係誒有關誒。
誒，依家有啲飛機唔能夠令誒喺機場咧，就係留太耐嘅問題。依個當然係同整個係誒機場本身個設施係需要進一步增加係好有關係。噉我依家嘢積極咧係增加緊一啲誒泊位，包括咗就除咗係誒所謂誒能夠有廊橋泊位啦。
同埋係誒遠程嘅泊位啦，咁噉，但係咧，我哋希望將來咧呢方面咧就係能夠有更加多嘅空間，畀多啲需要誒停留嘅飛機咧，就係可以停留。誒，我諗最後一個問題就係Sky Pier，誒，我哋依家嚟講咧就係冇計劃咧進一步誒擴大誒。
嗰個海天碼頭，因為我哋誒覺得咧，就誒海天碼頭咧係依家嘅嗰個設計容量係應都應該咧係可以嘅。
嚇！亦都另外咧，亦都因為咧，就誒大家都知道，喺嗰個環評煲入邊咧，都限制咗咧。其實我哋誒海天碼頭誒最高峯只能夠有幾多班船係可以誒，即係用嗰個海天碼頭。所以喺噉嘅情況之下，就算我哋擴建，都係冇乜誒誒作用。
好啊！阿善玉嘉怡。
主席，我首先搞清楚啲所謂報告先啦。咁因為咧，其實誒，我知道咧，個機管局自己都有個即係關於三跑嘅一個專門嘅網站。咁喺個網站裏邊咧，我亦都揾到一啲關於財務嘅評估嘅報告。誒，譬如話誒，頭先阿陳偉業問嗰個評估報告咧，我唔知係咪呢個。
網站以外嘅報告，你哋係仲有一啲係冇喺個，仲有啲報告係做咗而冇上載喺個網站裏邊嗱。我見到嘅關於財務最最新嘅報告就係誒匯豐銀行啊，HSBC做嘅，佢係應該係二零一一年做嗰個財務報告，五月三十一號。
個日子係五月三號，我唔知係咪嗰份報告以外仲有其他報告。如果根據嗰個嗰個報告咧，我嘅問題咧就係問咧，因為個報告裏邊講到咧，就喺佢嘅報告嘅十九頁咧就話個呢個嘅。
誒內部回報率咧個。
I.R.L.咧係大概三個percent噉樣樣，噉就同埋咧佢係誒，即係佢最撈屘一句，即係好簡單啦嚇，即係用大家用明白嘅就係the negative net present value and low I.R.L. leads to the conclusion that the free run free runway scenario does not generate a commercial rate of
Returned on a stand-alone basis and will only be justifiable for the Hong Kong government if the free runway scenario project delivers substantial economic benefits to the Hong Kong in addition to the financial return general for for AA。即係我嘅理解唔知係咪錯誤啦，即係其實即係話如果根據會方呢份報告咧，嗰
嗰個內部回報率三percent咧，其實嗰個財務嘅效益咧，其實已經唔係太過合理化去做一個有商業回報嘅一個三跑。咁當然啦，三跑可能會帶嚟一個所謂經濟嘅效益。咁而經濟嘅效益咧，就對整體香港有有有有。
好處噉嘅樣。不過佢其實後面都亦都提到同一份報告提到就係，如果嗰個即係當然啦，嗰個誒嗰個future passenger traffic，即係佢預測嗰個乘客嘅。
增長如果有所偏差咧，就可能對嗰個財務嘅風險係會加大等等。當然仲有頭先有同事都講到關於嗰個建築個成本噉樣。我想問民國報告除咗呢份之外，有冇其他？同埋係咪好似呢份報告所講，其實今次呢一個係政府叫機管局做啊，定係機管局自己都想做？因為
如果作單從財務效益嚟講，就唔係咁咁咁花算。咁但係經濟效益咧，即係帶嚟整體香港經濟效益咧，就你亦都做一份報告，二零一五年又話幾多錢啊噉樣樣，嗰啲就另計啦噉樣樣嚇。阿林總裁。
先啊，前議員講嗰啲係誒一啲舊嘅報告，係二零一一年當我哋嗰陣時做master plan二零三零嘅時候嘅一啲初步嘅一啲評估。誒當然響過去嗰幾年誒，我哋亦都響依誒各個方面咧都做咗一啲係update嘅。咁包括咗今年咧，我哋做咗個誒全新嘅一個誒。
財務報告咧都係由誒會豐做，噉我哋誒樂意遲啲咧為大家提供最新。即係而家未上載嘅，因為未上載。O K，好好。咁如果係噉，主席，我我我覺得係我都希望啦，佢能夠將最新嘅評估，我哋唔使睇翻啲幾年前報告噉樣樣。咁等我哋原本就預咗可能響下一次，當我哋討論到誒誒。
我哋整個項目嘅嗰個財務安排嘅時候提出啦，咁如果大家有興趣嘅，我哋可以早啲提出，好啊。
有冇跟進？
誒，其實佢未答我問題嘅喎，即係我問題就係咪機管局今次其實係你主係你主動做啫，係係係主係政府誒想你做啊？定你覺得就喺個即係如果根據匯豐嗰個報告，其實冇乜財冇乜財務效益嘅啫。噉你都你都覺得值得做誒？我哋最新做嘅嗰個誒。
財務報告嚟講咧，就覺得誒，我哋依一個項目係嗰個誒，可以話個賽嗰個商業效益啊，會會會唔會係會畀依個係係有明顯嘅嘅分別？咁誒，我哋到時樂意咧，就為大家提供個報告嘅時候，我哋再討論。
好啊，阿胡志偉議員。
代主席，可能我哋睇親嗰啲都係舊嘅報告，所以冇啲update啊，即係都比較上論盡。咁所以我以下提問咧，都可能係啲舊報告嘅係資料嚟嘅。咁但係都我諗我哋只能夠揸住呢啲資料問啦。譬如話，我哋睇得到喺誒預計會用嘅係填海嘅方。
法咧係呢個深層水泥半合法。
咁而呢個方法咧，誒根據報告所講咧，其實佢嗰個對。
誒整體嘅水質嘅影響咧，其實就得唔到證實嘅，因為佢有啲trial可能試過，但係大規模運用嘅時候咧，究竟實際效果點樣樣咧就未有證實嘅。咁呢啲會唔會係對即係真係落實嘅時間係令到就係所選擇嘅方嘅填海方法咧，係影響到？
環評報告嘅執行嘅情況，而影響到最終嘅工程造價咧。咁呢一個，我諗係即係可能機管局係進一步去解釋清楚呢一點，因為其實我哋見到，譬如著港珠澳大橋嘅填海咧，其實都往往因為就係個填海方法嘅選擇，到最後咧係可能同呢個環評報告嘅選，即係嗰個批。
批評啊，或者係要求咧，係有衝突嘅時間咧，係引領公眾對嗰個嘅係做法咧係有疑問嘅。咁咁同樣嘅情況喺填海裏邊，最重要當然係講緊即係海沙嗰個購買啦。咁而海沙購買已經係即係據瞭解啦，譬如好似港珠澳大橋嗰個人工島嘅填海嘅沙料咧。
都一路都係講緊係其中一個元元素咧，係影響到個工程進展嘅，咁而。
三跑道嘅填海工程咧，嗰個規模係要比港珠澳大橋嗰個人工島上面填海咧個規模大，可能係四倍五倍都唔定嘅。嗰個沙料嗰個來源係唔係能夠secure到咧？個來源secure唔到嘅時間，咁有啲咩嘅應對嘅方法咧？呢啲應對嘅方法。
係唔係會牽涉到即係嗰個嘅係工程成本嘅進一步上升咧？呢亦都係下一個問題，就係話我見到即係好多時喺呢工程預算裏邊咧，其實係將誒。
誒delay recovery measures，即係啲追趕落後嘅工程嘅安排咧，係擺咗喺裏邊嘅，但係就唔係擺喺個工程造價裏邊嘅。咁因此就話呢delay recovery measures其實到最後同個工程嘅係即係造價嘅關係會點樣樣咧？係咪呢個合約上邊係可以做得更加有效嘅監管咧？
咁誒到最後就係話。
因為大家都見到咧三跑個工程咧，可能都迫在眉睫啦。如果對按照機管局嘅講法，好緊張啦。咁而家我哋睇呢啲資料嘅時間，係咪應該從一個就話工程嘅安排咧，係會從一個廿四小時全面開工嘅角度咧，係去考慮去作為一個基本嘅參數。
去理解就係話，所謂工程進度嘅安排個基本嘅base line咧，就係以一個廿四小時全面運作嘅形式去處理，同埋咧係會全面投入相關嘅機器啊、人力嘅資源噉樣樣。噉我諗呢度亦都要進一步向公眾解釋翻，就係話你係咪能夠喺個市場上邊咧係吸納到呢一類。
嘅機器同埋呢個係即係人力嘅資源，因為如果唔係，你要重掏呢一個好似港鐵嘅問題，就係話到其時寫翻嚟報告就話我哋喺市場吸納唔到呢啲機器同埋呢個人力嘅時候咧，就會令到工程漸延唔落。咁所以我諗呢幾個固定嘅元素都請基本去打搭，多主席好啊。誒，總裁你有三秒答曬好誒。
就嗰個深層誒，即係誒水泥半合法咧，其實已經係得到誒環保處嘅誒嗰個誒誒批准㗎啦。咁所以喺我哋個E.I.入邊咧，其實已經係規定我哋要用呢個方法。噉我哋都係好關注呢個方法本身係咪可行。所以其實過去嗰段時間，我哋都做咗好幾。
次嘅嗰個trial，咁呢個trial之後嘅成績，我哋係好滿意嘅。噉我哋覺得呢個方法係可以一方面可以做到我哋嘅需要啦，亦都可以咧就喺環環保方面可以達到要求。咁第二咧海沙噉啊，其實過去嗰誒一段時間咧，我哋已經積極同誒內地相關部門喺度咧就討誒即係商討有關誒入。
口海沙嘅嗰個問題，咁依一個嘅進度都係誒，我哋覺得係誒滿意嘅。噉就誒最三最後一個問題咧，就當然係誒我哋誒依家做嘅依個預算入邊咧，都係預咗有一啲嘅礦天鑽石。噉我哋希望當然唔需要用到啦。咁但係我哋覺得依個誒。
誒預算都係合理嘅，副主席。
I've got a question for you, Mr. Poole. In the EI report, it states that the method that will be used is the non-dredge reclamation method, which is what now you say will be used as part of the reclamation. And I see that in paragraph nine, for example, of the Leshko paper, one of the method is the
Deep cement mixing, right. So I just want to confirm that the deep cement mixing is part of the non dredged reclamation method that is mentioned in the EI report. That's number one. Number two, in paragraph nine of the paper, you mentioned that there's been a series of trials that has been conducted by by your engineers to to
Ensure that the deep cement mixing method, which is a new method, is workable. So, can you give us the complete reports and tests of that trials that you've conducted to show us that this method, the deep cement mixing method, is indeed workable?
And it is not going to be a repeat of what the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge has experienced in their reclamation problems. So that's my my first question. Mr. Poole. Okay, certainly. In terms of, I can confirm very very clearly that DCM was included in the analysis on the EIA and it is a non-dredge method, absolutely.
The first trial that we did was in fact during the I.A. to establish, and it was monitored by A.P.D. as well, to make sure that we can show that it works without impacting on the environment as a non-dredge method. And so those trials that those trials were done in the I.A. and those reports, I'm sure, can be available. The
current trials we've done this year are more on the engineering side, but again we've taken the opportunity to do extensive environmental monitoring to show that in a bigger scale that the the process is still acceptable under the EIA. I think those are the reports which a lot of the NGOs are interested in. The recent trials and tests which
做過。
其實應該已經有一份係更新咗嘅。咁其實你今次應該要拎埋嚟，因為嗰個其實係就係我哋今日正正要討論嗰個問題啊嘛。成個計劃係唔係財政上係可行？嗰個誒成本會唔會虧蝕等等？點解你今日唔攞上嚟咧？我我我低提副主席咧，就係誒下一次我哋會講個財政嘅。
今次我哋討論呢樣嘢，其實都需要依一個資料。即係啊，誒誒，總裁，所以我會後誒會為大家提供一個要誒報告，因為我哋原本嘅嗰個計劃就以為話應該下一次嘅嗰個會度先討論誒財務安排。咁誒，大家對依個報告有興趣，我哋會盡快提供。盡快提供啦，好嘛？好嘛？O K。
咁而家就第一次就問完啦。噉我就頭先講咗咧，就我就會處理咗啊。國家奇援個動議，國家奇援，我畀兩分鐘你講講。
多謝主席。嗱，即係大家都聽得好清楚咧。其實頭先嗰個答問咧，最重要嗰幾點，政府係完全冇應，或者機管局都冇。
就係話點樣去確保個工程咧，係能夠唔會超支，唔會同重濤高鐵或者港珠澳大橋嘅覆設。
呢一啲嘅空口嘅承諾咧，即係頭先講嗰啲餐餐都係咁㗎啦。每一次上嚟嘅時候，就話我哋有幾嚴密嘅監察。
誒，我哋嗰啲模型計算咧係冇問題。
而家我哋發生緊嘅就係港珠澳大橋又要延遲，分分鐘難未。
高鐵咧就琴日先至爆出嚟咧，係一個接近二百億嘅超支，然後就政府仲要嗰兩嗰幾樣嘢都未起完嘅。
嗰啲大白象工程咧。
未完成，而家就要急急上馬。呢個我要講，呢一啲係即係推香港人落去海，即係呢啲係唔需要去做嘅嘢。其實。
所有嘅，譬如包括係嗰啲誒法定嘅程序，空場嘅一個談談判。
嗰啲詳細嘅經濟嘅分析都未拎到上嚟，我哋都未傾。
點解會發生呢一樣嘢咧？咁同埋頭先，我好覺得即係副局長講講啲嘢不負責任，佢講到好似又唔關佢事噉。
機管局心知肚明，政府全資擁有嘅，佢請你嗰時，總裁就係要你做呢樣嘢啊嘛。
即係要啃呢一單嘢啊嘛！咁政府就講到唔關佢事，佢自己計數嘅。其實呢樣嘢就絕對離譜。機管局所有嘅錢都係納税人嘅錢。
佢係要又要借，都係香港人要去幫佢還債。嗰啲分嗰啲利息，其實應該落翻去庫房做其他嘅工作，一毫子都係納税人嘅錢，唔係好似你咁講係機管局嘅。機管局係點樣會嚟㗎？食就爆出嚟嘅，即係我覺得政府噉樣去做咧，係不負。
責任唔係叫你完全唔起，而係起碼喺呢一個階段。
唔清唔楚嘅情況之下，唔好急於去做。國家期議員時間到啦，有冇人要就國家期議員嘅動議發言？
一分鐘，陳偉業。
我覺得咧，就誒。
如果大家記得，即係以前喺機場嗰陣時嗰個嘅審批程序同埋嗰研究程序咧，係好全面、好嚴謹嘅。噉就誒，政府似乎喺諮詢同埋喺討論過程裡面咧，係極度粗疏啊！噉啊，呢個小組成立，畀啲機會大家去睇啦。但係啲問題，
提都未睇完咧，好多工程即係嗰個嘅工作咧，已經係上咗馬，即係話你而家偷步係嘛？呢個係好不負責任嘅做法。噉我呼籲政府應該咧就即係成個三跑嘅工程咧，包括呢個罕獻啊同埋其他即係研究嗰方面咧，即係應該要暫停。
等我哋攞曬啲報告，包括已經完成咗嘅財務研究啊、工程可行性研究嗰啲咧，我哋呢個小組決定曬之後咧，至好進行。如果唔係嘅話咧，即係我覺得呢個係一個極為不負責任嘅態度咧，同埋會令到呢個公堂咧係不斷呢個被即係倒落呢個鹹水海係嘛海豚嘅問題。
而家得翻一隻嘅就已經係，就嚟香港嘅吉祥。長務業，理財人員。
即係其實最第一樣嘢咧，就係而家政府或者機機管局都係諗住霸王硬上弓㗎啦。
即係根本，即係錢又唔係你哋嘅嚇，一千四百幾億，到時要加又好，就算唔加。
其實一千四百幾億都好得人驚。
大家諗下，高鐵而家八百幾億。
而家講緊呢一個嘅三跑係一千四百幾億，就算你唔超支一千四百幾億。
都係即係納税人嘅錢。
到時咧。
如果解決唔到，尤其解決唔到空域問題咧，更加又係變咗另一個廢跑道。
好似高鐵而家都係止落，搞唔掂一地兩檢就變咗廢鐵。將來呢個誒三跑搞唔掂個空域，就變成一個廢道、廢跑道。
即係如果噉樣樣，即係納税人啲錢噉樣倒落鹹水海發咧，噉我哋覺得係非常之遺憾，亦都更加遺憾，佢係唔使過立法會去通過攞錢。胡志偉議員，多謝主席。
就郭家麒議員嘅係動議咧，其實係好重要，講咗一個觀點咧，就係而家喺我哋香港有嘅各項嘅基建工程咧，係相當多同埋龐大嘅。
喺唔同嘅工程裏邊出現嘅超支咧，政府歸根結底都仍然講就係話人手不足啊、物料短缺啊或者技術困難等等嘅問題。呢啲問題會係重新係喺翻呢個機場三跑個工程上出現嘅。咁所以今日嘅動議咧，其實係希望政府咧要小心去規劃呢啲工。
工程係避免多個工程同時進行嘅時候，而令到搶高造價，其他嘅工程咧係會進一步延誤同超支，而令到我哋市民嘅負擔咧係只會白上加斤。再者就係喺好多呢啲大型工程上邊咧，其實都經常碰到。
洗濕個頭之後咧。
加碼去完成工程，所以趁住三品未正式開工之前，如果能夠調整工程嘅安排嘅話，係對個社會更加有利嘅，多主席。善用佳言。
主席啊，關於個財務安排上面咧，運房局似乎有一局兩制喺呢一個高鐵咧。政府就話誒叫呢一個誒地鐵公司就派翻一百九十五定九十六億，然之後咧就向財委會申請誒畀翻呢一個誒呢個工程費用噉樣樣。
噉啊，即係左袋交翻畀右袋，右袋交交嚟畀翻左袋。但係喺呢一個誒三跑呢度咧，政府又冇呢一個處理方法，噉我都覺得好奇怪。點解又唔係要求呢一個誒基本局派息畀翻政府，政府又再透過財委會去誒抌翻落去呢個三跑道咧？
咧噉樣樣。
好啊！噉就有冇其他議員想發言？
陳陳能不如。
陳能畢業完。
係有啦，係誒嗱，其實我哋香港各項大型工程咧，基本上都係誒完工有個期㗎，咁誒除非有好大delay啦，咁誒我哋睇到港島嘅兩條鐵路咧，都係誒即係會逐步落成，跟住咧就誒即係觀塘延線又會落成啦，噉我。
我我就希望即係政府咧，係喺日後可唔可以誒進行呢啲大型工程嘅時候咧，進行一啲人手嘅評估啊。咁誒，譬如話機場，若果我哋喺誒動工啊嗰啲時間咧，係配合得好嘅話咧，咁都可以誒，即係避免大量工人咧因為工程完咗而失業嘅。咁所以我希望即係。
誒政府日後如果係誒去進行呢類工程嘅時候，都應該要顧及到人手嘅問題。不過咧，就係誒，如果係機場咧，我哋見得到，如果而家去開始去鋪排、去安排，甚至乎咧去誒動工咧，都係誒要一啲時間嘅。咁所以，我哋覺得喺人手安排上面，應該都唔會有好大嘅問題。
噉啊！如果政誒，點北上業？
主席，我係貧民委員會嘅委員。我哋嗰個退休保障計劃就快出爐，其中咧大家都聽到啦，有一個咩有經濟需要，一個就叫做誒，不論貧富。
事實上咧，無論邊個方案都好咧，我哋將來嗰啲福利支出都係唔會話一百年都唔爆煲嘅。
佢好多時咧就建基於我哋將來嗰啲所謂經濟增長，而經濟增長同埋生產力係絕對同基建有關。
我哋香港呢幾年喺度節節騰騰，蹉跎咗好多歲月。好多啲大型基建工程係可以令到我哋嘅前景同我哋嘅經濟增長同埋我哋嘅競爭力、我哋嘅生產力去提升嘅話咧，全部慢曬落嚟。再咁搞落去，我唔知將來香港仲有啲咩人。
住，所以我係反對最拖呢件嘢。
至於話點樣監管啊時間啊同埋費用方面，我係絕對支持要做得好。我遲啲會發言講呢一方面，姚思榮議員。
睇到周邊嘅機場都起緊啦，係嘛？珠三角好，誒，包括上海、北京都係講緊第三、第四條跑道。噉我哋而家仲係講緊第三條跑道嘅話咧，即係應應應該盡快噉嘅上馬，係嘛？如果二零二三年誒起好咧，都係遲㗎啦。如果我哋今次，
再去拖將個時間拖後嘅話咧，香港根本上咧，我從旅遊物流方面咧都真係折騰唔起嚟，所以我覺得咧，誒，我哋議員咧希望從嗰個香港經濟方面考慮，同我哋香港旅遊業個角度考慮，避免咧即係將個問題誒再誒誒拖延。
咁所以咧，我係反對呢一次嘅建議嘅。易建明議員。
啊，多謝主席。啊，兩件事，第一，我係申報誒，我係機管局嘅成員啦。第二咧，就係誒，我哋覺得誒，就算物流呢個業界咧，認為呢個誒第三跑道嘅嘅誒構建咧，係非常之重要。
我哋香港除咗我哋個金融體係嚇之外咧，而家最有競爭力嘅咧就係我哋嘅機場。如果我哋唔能夠保持佢喺呢個誒龍頭嘅位置嘅話咧，對於我哋成個物流同埋呢個貿易咧個業務咧，都會有相當大嘅影響。所以我係反對國家奇議員呢個議案。盧偉國議員。
主席嘅發言咧係反對國家嘅議員呢一個議案嘅，因為誒機場嘅擴建咧，其實經過多番嘅諮詢、多番嘅論證。
就而家呢一個三跑道嘅系統咧，亦亦都經過咧好多即係誒環境嘅評估，而最終咧獲得呢個誒環評嘅通過。
誒當然亦都有加埋有啲即係條件咧，即係舒緩呢個對環境影響。咁誒頭先我剛才發言咧，亦都有提過咧，其實係喺目前雖然話好多工程咧去到施工高峯期，但係咧有啲新嘅前瞻性一啲嘅大型基建項目咧，其實嘅開展係相當相當緩慢。
噉係誒工程業界咧係係支持呢個三跑道系統嘅，啊大部分我接觸嘅工程師都係有同樣嘅睇法嘅，咁所以咧我係即係反對咧係對呢個項目咧再進一步拖延啊！多謝主席。謝偉全議，多謝主席。誒當然咧，我同其他即係議員同事都係好關。
住咧三跑嘅工程嗰個誒個工程使個錢啊，同埋個時間方面嘅監控啊，同埋係咪用得誒啱咧等等嚇，尤其是咧而家我哋好多即係大型嘅。
誒呢個誒基建嘅工程咧，都係出現超支超時啦。咁所以我頭先咧就呢個問題都問咗，即係政府咧，即係運房局佢哋擔當咩角色？當然我對於即係誒阿邱副局長嘅答覆咧，我係非常失望嘅，似乎咧畀人感覺我哋唔使理㗎啦。
靠機管局得㗎啦，噉樣呢樣嘢係完全唔負責任嘅政府。咁但係噉，因為呢個三跑咧對未來嘅經濟咧，香港係有長遠嘅影響，亦都係非常重要嘅。所以咧，我就係唔可以支持郭家麒嘅動議。誒，Jeff，誒林建峯議員。誒，多謝主席。誒，我申報。
我係機管局嘅誒董事，誒我都係反對阿郭家麒議員呢個動議嘅。佢哋同埋一班人成日咧就喺度投訴，我哋而家香港有啲班次唔夠多啊，我哋香港機場唔夠方便啊，同時間咧就要同時間咧就響阻止我哋第。
三條跑道嗰個興建，依啲都唔係我哋香港市民願見到嘅。依啲為反對而反對，其實即係裏邊講嗰啲理由咧。如果唔夠人就乜都唔好做啦，係嘛？噉我哋想辦法去解決佢啊嘛。咁依個先至係一個理性去處理我哋香。
香港面對問題嘅方法嚟嘅，即係即係反對。
建築材料嚟嘅海沙，海沙而家個價錢咧，可以越嚟越貴㗎。依個需求咧係越嚟越大㗎。你而家唔去做，係啊，第一有可能買海沙都有一個問題嚟㗎。咁所以咧。
都係我唔支持啊！郭嘉琪呢個建議，黃定光議員。
誒香港海運已經由誒第一位一路下降，剩翻空運嘅優勢咧，而家我哋仲存在。若果而家我哋唔發展三跑嘅話，啊，將來嘅話，我諗進修界咧係極極力會支持。
擔跑嘅，盡快投入建築。
張華峯議員，啊，阿主席啊，嗰個香港作為國際大都會、國際金融中心，如果我哋喺交通基建度唔能夠配合嘅話，我哋點樣能夠咧？即係嗰個推薦係國際性嘅會議喺香港開咧？我諗咧呢個三第三跑道咧。
係非常之緊迫，所以我哋希望咧呢個三跑嘅機場跑道咧盡快開工。唔該，陳建波議員。
我諗誒要開呢個或者開展呢個機場三跑嘅工程咧，係好多香港人嘅共識，亦都明白係對香港個重要性。請你唔好自言自語啊！所以我覺得咧就誒，即係我對啊羅家奇議員呢個我係絕對反對，因為咧呢個真係對香港好重要。如果我哋有咩困難，我哋咪去解決佢咯嚇。但係個方向就一定要。
多謝主席。廖長江議員，係主席誒，無論係喺財務安排或者係工程或者環保方面咧，我相信每一位委員都有好多疑問，但係我哋冇理由係因為喺目前嘅階段咧，因為工程人手可能不足或者物料短缺嘅話，就叫停整個項目嘅。我係反對呢個國家議員。
仲有冇同事想發言？
啊，謝謝你。
國家旗啊，佢個睇法，但係國家旗嘅睇法咧係係有選擇中嗰個嘅角度去睇嘅，但係依個第三跑係我哋係冇，因為從香港喺個經濟環境好、生存嘅環境，我係冇得選擇，所以我好希望國家旗收回翻依個誒，依個誒建。
而出嚟咧嚇，噉我覺得咧大家都係容易做啲，因為我哋喺依方面係為咗香港嘅生存係要做第三條跑道啊！多謝主席。何俊仁議員是否想發言？
講兩句啦。咁其實咧，誒手上面咧，就郭家麒議員咧，就我明白佢嘅睇法嘅。工程人手不工程人手不足啦，物料短缺啦，技術困難。但係咧，做人應該見到問題咧，係應應該諗辦法去解決，而唔係話見到呢啲問題咧，我哋繞路走。噉樣咧，我哋好多嘅問題咧，都會令到香港停滯不前嘅。噉我哋覺得。
應該政府啊，同埋機管局咧，係應該提供一個解決辦法嘅誒一個方案出嚟。噉我哋議員審完啦，覺得唔合理，咁咪再諗另外諗諗其他嘅渠道去處理咯。即係可能甚至啊，郭嘉琪再拎翻個議案上嚟。咁但係如果我哋乜嘢都唔做，咁咪其實係應該係第二次開會啫嘛。上次係選主席。
噉就今次真係真正開會，我哋第一日開始就話叫停嘅話咧，其實唔係一個實事求是嘅一個解決辦法，所以我哋今日係反對今次今次係二項嘅，多謝主席。今今今次唔係第一次開會，第三次開會嘅啊。
啊啊，國家議員，你誒是否想發言？一分鐘。
誒，我聽到好多啲議員咧，即係我希望歷史上都可以做一個記錄，因為咧就。
我哋唔止係錯一次，我哋係一錯再錯。即係政府喺推展呢一啲工程嘅時候，冇係思前想後。
我個動議咧係冇叫唔起，事實上佢係有好多嘅未解決嘅嘢。
亦都係好清楚，連嗰啲而家籤咗約、賠緊錢嘅工程咧，都未搞得掂。
點解喺呢個時候急啲乜嘢嘢？
你都知道籤咗落去啲嘢係改唔到嘅，承建商係有理由，亦都有喺合約寫咗寫咗清清楚楚，係會同你追討啲錢嘅。
而家高鐵咪噉樣，廣珠咪噉樣咯，日日同你攞一千幾百萬。
嗰啲係納税人嘅錢嚟。
即係我哋做喺立法會入邊有啲人放棄自己嘅天職，唔去監督政府嘅。
我係唔會覺得即係需要理佢，但係我希望咧，我哋呢個議案係通過咧，係代表維護香港所有市民嘅利益。你時間到啦，誒，現在係誒支持誒郭家麒議員，啊，郭家麒議員要求記名點票，點票鐘響五分鐘。
我去洗手間。啊，近五分鐘。
我呢個舉手嘅啫嘛，嚇舉手，但係我。
係。
本人同意，鑑於現時本港多個進行中的大型基建工程，特別是當局近日已承認港珠澳大橋工程將出現延誤。
原因包括工程人手不足、物料短缺。
及各項技術困難等，就此本人同意，在確定本港有足夠人力及建築物料前，先額後開展三跑機場三跑工程。
以免多個工程同時進行，搶高造價及令各項工程進一步延誤，最終增加市民負擔。
禁停嘅啫嘛，未啊！你想禁唔禁停啊？可以停，你可以停五分鐘，五分鐘。
應該係噉樣。
哦，你驚有。
睇曬。
都唔齊嘅，因為有啲人。
好啊。
係啊！我哋冇投票。
哦，冇問題。
佢自己嗰啲。
佢當第一輪咧。
我睇下。
唔係畀第一輪。
五分鐘要咁停。
依家講。
贊成郭嘉琪議員嘅動議，請舉手。
我讀咧。
啊，郭嘉琪、陳偉業、李卓仁、胡志偉同埋副主席。
反對嘅請舉手。
謝偉全、黃定光、誒誒張華峯、盧偉國、易志明、啊林建峯、石禮謙同埋啊啊郭佩凡啊，依邊就田北慎議員、啊陳建。
連波、何俊賢、廖翔。
江啊，姚思永同埋啊。
阿陳行斌。
十三個反對幾多個？十三位反對，五位支持，五位贊成，所以個議案係被否決嘅。誒，跟住阿田北辰議員舉咗手，誒要求發言誒問問題嘅係誒四分鐘嘅第一次。
啊，田北辰要。我想問下啊，副局長啊。
嗱，監察三堡工程咧，你哋都預咗一定係同。
高鐵呢個香港段比較啦，之前有誒同事講過啦。
噉啊！如果將來通過財委會開會咧，呢個機場擴建工程統籌辦有十一個人。
同埋有兩間顧問。
咁今日咧，高鐵咧路政署下邊咧就有十七個人。
同一個顧問。
而路政署嘅鐵路拓展處長咧，就公開話咧。
佢呢個小組係得嗰十幾個人嘅啫。
而港鐵本身有幾百個人。
所以咧，佢其實根本咧係靠佢哋。
誒，去提出報告嘅。
啊，噉啊，根本咧睇得出咧，其實佢係冇噉嘅人手啊，去做一個獨立嘅判斷，係依賴廣鐵。
噉啊，跟住最好笑啦！去到個顧問咯，噉我哋嘅調查委員會個顧問嚟咗啦。
噉啊，收咗八千五百萬。
咁咪揾佢係及住誒港鐵嘅，就話畀勞政主張。
咁再問落去咧，原來佢畀我哋嘅印象咧，就係原來政府問一句佢答一句，政府要查啲嘢佢就交代。
噉我問佢：你覺唔覺得你嘅職責係基本上係要盡你嘅能力幫助政府確保佢如期完成而唔超支咧？
噉佢話：誒係呢個係我認識嘅工作範圍。噉我跟住問佢：政府同港鐵開會，你有冇去啊？佢話佢冇。
個問官點解你唔去咧？佢話港鐵啊，政府冇邀請我去。
噉我問佢：你有冇自動堅持要出席嘅會議？如果你唔出席政府同港鐵嘅會議，你點幫政府監察港鐵咧？佢就話：嗱，呢個就好得意啊！佢話：我記唔起。
我記唔起有冇要求出席所有會議。
今日我想問嘅咧，就係而家其實有一個翻版嚟嘅。
不過咧。
佢哋係十七人，你又得十一，咁咪少咗六個。
不過咧，你啊多咗一間顧問公司，有兩間。
噉你準備呢兩個顧問公司，你係準備點用啊？你會唔會同佢哋講清講楚？唔係你問一句佢答一句。如果大家一早已經講清楚成個設計點，要幾耐時間，要幾多錢，佢兩間顧問公司你要寫埋落個約度嘅。呢兩間顧問公司如果有睇到有。
任何嘢，佢嘅責任係要盡快去提醒你哋去解決。唔係咧，你係扣錢嘅，你一個扣分制嘅。佢可能億八咧扣到後來乜都冇嘅，因為如果結果又超支又誒又延誤，而佢樣樣嘢其實都冇同你講嘅。
啊，咁呢個就第一個問題啦。你會唔會寫落呢個啊協議度？真係令到我哋下次啊見到呢顧問公司咧，唔會真係聽到好猛好猛，咪扣分就最簡單㗎啦。佢可能啊冇錢收添，億百元嘅嘢全部冇錢收。
第二樣嘢，你嗰十誒，你畀佢答咗你四分鐘嘅，你唔係啊，你問埋就六分鐘。嗱，我問埋先，你想十一個人會唔會包埋一個噪音專家？因為我極之極之關注三跑對於馬灣居民嗰個噪音嘅影響係差過今日，好過今日定係點？你會唔會？
有一位噪音專家，兩個問題。誒，局長。
誒主席，嗯，我呢度都想解釋誒清楚啦。頭先答你唔好解釋清楚啊！你得十秒鐘。誒主席，簡單嚟講咧就係噉樣樣，因為港鐵嚟本本身咧，佢用嘅誒，佢係用誒政府嘅錢嘅，佢喺誒建造高鐵嘅時候，而今次嚟講咧誒呢個機機場管理局咧係佢用自己本身嘅錢。
變咗咧，佢主要嚟講咧，佢對於自己嗰個監督嚟講係係好重要嘅。點樣控制？相對嚟講咧，我哋的確咧，誒，依我哋嘅啊統籌嘅辦公室嚟講咧，係唔係好似係勞政署咁咁多人？但係嗰個由於嗰個基本嗰個嘅誒模式係相當唔同下嘅，所以咧嗰個唔係一個翻版嚟嘅，即係絕對。
佢唔係一個翻版嘅情況。至於你頭先講嗰個嗰個誒，我哋嗰啲嘅誒M and V嘅顧問咧，究竟係點樣做咧？我哋一定會吸收翻高鐵本身嗰個經驗，然後睇到喺我哋委託佢嘅工作裏邊咧，點樣令到佢誒獲取資訊同埋佢個監督工作咧係誒誒，或者佢幫即係會有個溝。
錢制扣分制擺落去㗎，係咪？嗱，我哋我哋未去到嗰個地步，或者一陣間我請啊啊，我唔知。噉啊噉啊，最好有啦。主席可唔可以？有冇噪音專家？你個統籌辦有冇噪音專家？
誒主席，主席，我想解釋清楚咧，我哋呢一個嘅統籌辦公室咧，佢唔係做緊工程嘅嘅監督工作，工程監督工作都係基建局去做翻。咁即係所以你冇啦，係咪？你咪講冇。但係，但係我哋本身嘅專家嚟講，係令到佢咧，佢要確實地咧，係遵守翻咧，誒，協助我哋遵守翻咧，我哋喺環境。
評估裏邊咧嗰啲報告咧要求嘅各種嘅規定，咁都要有個環評專家㗎，主席，我係要求呢樣嘢啊。啊，誒，你係要求聽，不過即係頭先局長答咧，即係話使自己錢嘅就會慳啲嘅，使政府錢就可以即係使腳抹腳嘅。噉我諗政府要檢討下。阿阿阿阿阿阿主席啊，誒，好似未。
回覆佢，係啊！但係你你過曬時間啦，好嘛？阿林建峯議。
其實咧，即係依個誒小組委員會咧，係畀咗我哋一個好嘅機會咧，去問一啲大家都可能唔係好瞭解嘅問題。
即係我再睇翻嗰個國家旗嗰個動議咧。
佢又提到一啲人手不足啊、物料短缺啊、技術困難啊等等呢啲問題，我哋。
完全係可以響依度問嘅，即係唔通。
我哋見到個病人，嗰個病人。
啊！
有有個重症。
噉。
你話你技術唔夠啊，唔好醫佢啦，等技術夠先醫佢咩？死鬼咗啦，係咪啊？咁嗱，有幾個問題咧，我想問一問，我都希望局長直接啲去答。
嗱，人手不足呢個問題咧，大家都係關注嘅。咁大個工程，你點樣可以誒？可以誒？響人手方面做到好好嘅配合咧？咁當然呢啲係要同工程公司有一個好好嘅瞭解。啊，嗱，我正話亦都提過三廿個。
個問題，沙響填海咧係一個重要嘅原料嚟嘅。
啊，近期咧都啊，砂嗰個需求量都喺全球性嚟講都都幾高嘅，咁依啲都係。
市價嘅啫嚇，咁喺依一方面，我哋點樣係可以有足夠嘅填海原料嚇？喺價錢上邊咧，亦都係可以用一個合理嘅價錢去買到佢嘅。
咁誒，另外喺填海嗰個方式嗰度咧，而家係用一個好環保嘅方式去做填海嘅。咁喺評估誒依度會唔會出現一啲一啲技術上嘅問題啦？你知有啲人咧。
好中意走去J R㗎嘛？喺唔瞭解嘅情況之下咧，都走去J R㗎嘛嚇。咁所以咧，依啲咁嘢咧，你哋係要好清楚噉樣去解釋嚇，就唔好咧，即係令到嗰個啊工程咧係受到阻延嘅。
啊，顧家。
啊！主席就阿林議員幾個問題啦。嗯。
頭先譬如第三個問題指到嗰個嘅司法覆核，其實已經發生緊㗎啦。咁誒裏邊嘅司法覆核有有啲係啊針對緊啊環保署長本身嗰個發出嘅環評許可證啦，有啲係針對行政會議嘅決定啦，有啲爭爭嘅城規啦。每一個咧，我哋都會咧係去好啊認真噉樣樣咧，係去回。
應翻呢啲噉嘅司法複核嘅呢個係誒，我哋自己本身政府有責任去去去掃除一啲障礙，使到基金局係可以推行佢嘅工作。
啊！至於人手不足嘅問題咧，啊，我哋知道，當然而家嘅建築業係緊張嘅，咁所以咧，誒，我哋都係請咧，機管局方面咧，亦都係研究緊有冇咩方法，譬如點樣樣係咪可以通過補充外勞嘅呢啲計劃啊？如果唔係呢個補充計劃之外，仲有對咩方法啊，使到我哋嗰個人手上高咧係可以係啊能夠。
有充裕一啲噉，呢個係誒請佢哋亦都係考慮呢方面嘅。我相信從佢哋本身嗰個角度嚟講咧，佢哋都會喺度呢方面係思考。至於海沙方面，頭先阿林總裁都解釋咗，咁呢方面亦都需要政府一方面咧係啊，通過政府同政府之間係同誒內地嘅政府方面咧係做一啲溝通嘅噉。
咁誒，所以喺呢個項目裏邊，除咗機管局本身要做佢嘅功夫之外咧，其實我哋冇誒推卸到政府本身呢方面嘅工作。我哋亦都明白到咧，頭先議員講咗好多嘅關注，我哋亦都會認真咧將呢啲噉嘅關注咧，其實係要去做嘅。尤其是頭先有幾位議員都特別講關於。
於嗰個成本控制同埋嗰個工工工時工序嗰個問題嚇。
嗱，依家第二輪咧，我有啊填海嗰度咧，環保嗰度。
快快脆脆講講啊！誒填海嗰度頭先，如果誒針對翻誒填海嘅解釋啊，噉樣我相信誒頭先誒機管局嘅同事亦都解釋得清楚，佢哋盤開新嗰個填海上個方案點樣樣去對環境嘅影響嚟講咧，係減到最低。但係我哋呢度喺誒環評本身嘅司法複核裏邊個過程。
裏邊咧，我相信我哋都會好清楚噉樣向大家去申明嘅嚇。好啊！依家有三嗱，我又有誒陳偉業、郭嘉琪同埋阿田北辰三個問第二輪嘅，加埋李卓仁啊四個有冇睇啲？
啊，陳監林，你係第一次嘅，我畀你問先啦。但係我喺度要畫線㗎嚇。
O.K.，陳家華議員。誒，多謝主席。
即係我諗誒，三跑呢個問題咧，係牽涉到香港嘅。
未來嗰個經濟發展嘅問題嘅，即係如果我哋大家見到咧周邊嘅地區，
或者係鄰近啲國家咧，佢哋對於嗰個客運、貨運，
啊！嗰個發展咧，都係非常之迅速嘅。我哋如果係，
誒繼續停留喺現有嘅嗰個階段嘅話咧，相信未來嘅十年八年裏邊咧，香港嘅客運、貨運咧，甚至到旅遊業啊，其他嘅行業咧，都會受到好激烈嘅競爭，甚至到咧就係。
誒所謂不進則退嘅呢種現象咧，係非常之嚴重嘅。
咁所以三跑上馬咧係。
誒預先在言，大家都社會上都有好大嘅共識咧，希望可以盡快係上馬嘅。咁當然啦，社會上仍然都有一部分嘅人咧。
就係經常要提出一啲啊質疑嚇，噉啊，正如其他嘅嗰啲誒基建一樣咧，譬如話港珠澳大橋無端端又搞嗰個所謂司法嘅複核，導致到咧係拖慢咗一段相當長嘅時間，唔單止係時間嘅損失。
而且我哋喺公堂上面嘅嗰個開支嚟，都增加咗。
咁所以，我哋希望咧就係。
誒香港嘅議會或者香港嘅社會嘅誒市民咧，都能夠認清楚咧，我哋誒必須要發展咧，先至可以繼續維持香港嘅原有嘅競爭力。
如果唔係嘅話，呢個問題係相當令人遺憾嘅。
主席，我知道有同事咧係。
誒提出動議咧，就係誒想將呢一個。
誒計劃咧，暫時放低，要等至到人力成本嗰方啊，已經否決咗啦。我知道即時間係否決咗啦，但係呢一種係誒意圖阻撚我哋嘅基建咧發展嘅一個做法。
噉我相信咧喺現有嘅嗰個籌備嘅階段裏邊咧，仍然都仲有不少嘅啊，類似想阻撚呢一個項目推行嘅其他嘅行動。噉我亦都期望咧就係誒政府相關嘅部門咧，都必須有一個充足。
嘅嗰個準備，啊，因為如果萬一咧，呢一個嘅計劃。
不幸嘅被某一啲嘅勢力啊阻撓嘅話咧，咁可能造成嘅損失啊會更大嘅。政府係咪應該有其他嘅嗰個所謂準備咧？咁另外就係目前咧，我哋都見到咧有成五六個嘅司法複核喺手上面。
誒，如果呢啲司法覆係繼續係咁糾纏落去嘅話咧，好可能亦都會造成咧，我哋成個計劃推行嘅時候咧有所顧忌嘅。咁呢一方面，政府有咩嘅誒方法可以令到機管局咧喺推行嘅時候咧係更加順暢咧？
噉，即係我順順便想講講申報一下嘅就，我係機管局嘅啊非執董。好啊，多謝主席。
啊！主席啊，我啊，頭先啊，陳議員提嘅好多嘅觀點啦嚇，我都好認同佢嘅誒誒分享，同埋佢嘅擔心嘅。嗯誒，不過咧，即係誒，我相信喺市民嚟講，當然佢哋亦都係，如果佢有權係提出一啲嘅司法上嘅嘅質疑嘅話咧，當然佢哋可以咁做，但係我都。
覺得咧誒，亦都係同方同樣地咧，係應該去睇香港本身嘅總體嘅大局咧，係作為出發。咁所以，如果一啲嘅誒不合理據嘅一啲嘅司法上嘅挑戰咧，我哋一定係會係據理力爭，同埋去為我哋本身誒機場能夠係擴建咧，係去誒做好我哋本身嘅準備同埋司法上嘅。
誒誒，回應嘅好啊！第二輪有四位嘅，咁但係因為時間問題啊，一分鐘連問連答，做個簡單嘅問題好嘛？陳偉業議員，我主席，我希望主席即係同秘書研究下咧，睇下會唔會將即係廿年前即係立法當年立法局做呢個機場審嗰個研究小組嗰陣時咧，就就翻究竟當時有。
有啲咩報告提供咗嘅啊？揾翻啲報告名列出嚟啦，同埋當時有幾個問題係研究邊幾個範圍嘅，最好就即係列咗出嚟咧。我諗呢個委員會其實可以按翻當年嗰個嘅即係範圍咧進行較為仔細嘅研究啊。噉我覺得呢個對好多委員嚟講，同埋對公眾嚟講咧都會。
會有些少嘅幫助。
好啊！誒，郭家麒員，主席係主席係咪會做啊？主席誒，我叫秘書去研究下會做到啦，係咪？
係就頭先咧就好多啲誒技術上嘅，包括啦，譬如話個工程入邊咧涉及嗰啲嘅人力嘅安排啦，嗰個物料嘅安排啦，海沙嘅安排咧，我就希望有文件補翻畀我哋，呢個第一。第二咧就主席，我就知道咧下下一次會就講嗰個財務啦，但我希望咧。
就誒，盡快咧。
因為今日都問咗好多嗰啲資料咧，就應該機管局又好，政府又好咧，都攞翻一啲實際嘅一啲數據嘅。特別係點樣可以令到嗰個工程咧係喺指定嘅時間同埋指定嘅誒資金嗰度去去做得到。噉啊，如果你話要説服立法會，
係信納你哋嗰個論據，我相信呢一即係今次嘅文件。
呢一啲咁粗造嘅一啲嘅簡簡介咧，就冇可能㗎啦，公眾亦都唔會收貨嘅。噉我希望即係機管局。
就算你係計錯數都好，你早少少同我哋講嘅話咧，到時個責任都唔喺你嗰度。
田北十元。
一分鐘咧就我唔Q你啦，我純粹就係講我開出嘅一啲嘅條件，希望你哋考慮下，嗯。
嗰個請顧問負責以下工作，你寫咗A、B、C、D。
但係，我想你考慮埋加個E。
就係話咧，確保三跑完成之後咧，佢對馬灣居民嘅夜晚嘅噪音嘅影響唔差得過今日。
OK，呢個咧就唔係擺咗落去咩符合法律規定嘅，你可能覺得今日嘅噪音符合法律規定，但係馬灣住嘅居民絕對唔同意呢樣嘢。
第二咧就係請呢兩個顧問個合約擺一個扣分制喺度，即係話佢A、B、C、D加埋我希望將來有E，你要畀個評分佢，佢做成點？base上我個評分如果全部合格咧，你就畀個九千萬九千萬；如果唔係咧，就一路。
扣落去，扣到可能零。
好嘛，希望你哋考慮。好啊，阿李卓仁議員。
即係主席，頭先我聽到副局長講話會同中國政府傾嗰個海砂問題，其實即係想我想知道想傾啲咩嘢咧，因為其實價格本身都係市場嘅啫。嚇，當然可能同佢傾就係話可唔可以開放多啲地方畀人去啊採石，咁可能係依樣嘢咧。咁但係採咗之後，咁都係照照要。
賣嘅啫，噉我一攞去大家去睇翻海沙，去查下而家嘅情況，其實根本一路暴漲緊嘅海沙價價格，所以我真係覺得海沙依樣嘢係一個好嚴重嘅一個，即係誒成個計劃其中一個好好容易會超支嘅一個項目嚟嘅嚇。噉我想問下同中誒中國政府有？
咩傾下，局長？
主席，我簡單嚟講啦，就係其實我哋由於知道誒，我哋需要大量嘅海沙啦。咁誒喺我哋香港比較近嘅範圍裏邊咧，其實主要喺誒內地其中一個主要嘅來源啦。當然我哋都唔完全排除有其他地方嘅嚇。咁但係誒，既然香港如果喺運輸嚟講比較近咧，喺內地咧，我哋希望能夠。
對呢個海砂嘅供應咧係有一個穩定嘅嚇。好啊，噉就誒，我提醒同事，下次咧就喺誒明年嘅一月五日誒星期二八點半至到十點半舉行嘅。噉我哋又係講嗰個財務嘅安排嘅。咁亦希望政府同埋機管局盡早畀曬啲。
充足資料等議員有充份嘅時間去睇，好嘛？OK，咁今日會議到此為止。誒，多謝各位。