唔緊要，唔緊要，嚇噉啊！邀請團體入嚟啊，唔該。
佢唔係團體㗎啦。
唔該，可以請律師。
welcome。
Okay, thank you, representatives of the law society for coming. I think we all know each other, so there's no need for introductions. Before we allow members to ask questions, would you like to add anything to the the papers and the rules that has been tabled at Legislative?
Mr. Chairman, thank you for inviting us to attend this panel discussion.
I don't think we have got anything to add, but of course we are here to answer any questions that your members may have. But for the information of this panel, the Law Society Council has considered.
嗯。
implementing the LOP as soon as practicable, and we're aiming for the commencement day.
You know, hopefully, first day in January two thousand and sixteen. Great. So it's very crucial that we get all the subsidy legislation to be clear, complete.
We understand that the Order Eighty One or the rules of the High Court and the rules of District Court.
It's going to be amended in due course. It's going to be gazetted very soon.
Yes, I've read your letter dated the twenty-nine of June, two thousand and fifteen to this panel. It's a Leishgo paper CP CB four one two six eight oh one. But I think we have some queries about what exactly is the status of.
Order 81， is it now before the chief justice or what?
This is they have been sent to the rules committee by the Department of Justice for signing. And after they've been signed, they will be passed back to the DOJ to arrange for gazette. When would that take place? We've been informed that the by because we've got representatives on the rules committee.
And we've been informed that the rules have been signed. Okay, so it's just a matter of formality that they be gazetted as soon as possible. That's right. Yeah. Okay. All right.
委員有冇咩問題啊？
或者我問先啊，嗯。
As I've mentioned before, directly there there are no direct questions on these arising from these rules or papers, but.
I have been receiving a lot of comments and and perhaps complaints from members of the legal profession regarding the arrangement for insurance, especially the professional indemnity insurance issue. That every year they've been asked to to make a very substantial payment by by way of premium or otherwise.
and I understand the law society or the PIS has been giving substantial discount, one third discount to members, but it is my duty to relay the concerns of members of the profession, and to ask that the law society do consider whether there is sufficient funds in the surplus right now. There's two point, I think the current surplus.
是2.1 billion dollars， and whether that is enough to justify a further reduction of insurance payment by members of the legal profession， because it is a big payment， especially for smaller firms and practitioners， individual practitioners。 so I hope to relay this concern to the law society。
I know this is not exactly the occasion to talk about insurance, but since we are dealing with limited liability partnership top-up insurance rules, perhaps I raise that issue with you.
If I can just briefly reply to that, and certainly it's something which will be noted and passed on to the Law Society Council. Just going back a few years, just for the information of members, I think it's as recent as the year 2000 that the fund itself was was effectively banked.
bankrupt， because we had a lot of large claims， two very very large conveyancing claims in particular， and also due to the fact that one of the reinsurers of the scheme went bankrupt in 1998。
and at that time, we actually were forced to make a call upon the members because the fund, which is a statutory scheme, as you're aware.
requires fixed payments to be made in accordance with the mechanism of the scheme, but in addition we had to exercise our power, and as far as I'm aware it's the only time in history we ever did that, to make a further call upon members.
and I think because of that we've been extremely prudent, because there was a strong desire to make sure that that would never have to happen again, and through very very careful management of the scheme, through our appointed fund managers, and through the corporation directors, we have arrived at a.
situation now where we do have a considerable surplus.
那係 allowed us due to an amendment in the rules which took place just before the retirement of the the last chief justice.
to which gave us the power for the first time to make reductions, and the issue is considered on an annual basis by the Law Society Council when it comes time for calling for payments. Four out of the last five years, we've been able to grant a 33 and 1/3%
reduction.
and.
We do, I can assure you, take on board the comments of the managers and the recommendations of the fund managers as to exactly what a surfeit, what should be done with the surplus and what kind of surplus we do need to ensure that we would never have to make that call upon.
members again, and with continued prudent management in the future, it is not impossible that we would see even bigger reductions to the premiums which are levied in the future, based if the law society correctly exercises discretion. We're aware that for smaller firms,
It is a considerable sum. We are, of course, the only profession that has to carry compulsory insurance. None of the other professions have it imposed upon them by the legislature.
所以我們非常獨特，在這方面。
它 does amount to a considerable contribution, but one also has to bear in mind that the welfare of the public is being protected here by the contributions to the scheme.
Based on personal experience, I can say that probably on average it cost about sixty thousand dollars to for a contribution for a firm with a clear claims record, which if one breaks that down to say five thousand dollars per month.
It is not an enormous sum for the solicitors to bear.
所以，使得公眾可以 adequately 保護。
Thank you for those comments. I look forward to seeing further reductions, if possible, given the surplus you have now. Let me finish. Hi, Mr. Smith, may you wear the headphones? Sure. Yeah.
嗯。
係好多謝，好多謝幾位啊出席我哋今日嘅研討會啦！啊呢呢個委員會啦，咁咧我哋每一個人，OK，誒第幾台啊？
no，it's not coming through。
是第二個頻道，我諗。Yeah， this is what I have.
都係我哋嘅問題。
the volume.
yes, okay, take your time. Thank you. I have it now. Okay. Thank you. Apology.我哋咧都知道呢個委員會而家傾緊嘅係關於啊法律服務嘅規則，但係我哋喺呢一度每個人都係有兩兩帽嘅。一個咧就係我哋三位啱啱都係法律界嘅背景，但係我哋咧亦都要考慮公眾利益個。
個問題，咁所以咧，我諗喺呢一度咧，我想係誒清楚少少嗱，即係喺而家呢個修訂條例裏邊係誒明確咗咧，只要符合若干條件。
咁一啲我哋認為係啊清白嘅，即係冇犯錯嘅合夥人咧，就無需再係因為嗰個合夥誒裡面有其他成員嘅失責行為，負上個人嘅法律責任。
嚇！呢個係一個重點。噉我首先咧，想喺呢一度你哋誒講清楚所謂若干條件。
係誒乜嘢嘅情況底下？
就係屬於呢個若干條件。
嚇！呢個咧，我哋考慮就係客户嘅權益嘅問題嚇，噉係可唔可以喺呢度清楚啲？
嚟定乜嘢係若干條件？
嗯。
好多謝阿梁議員嘅剩係個誒提出嘅嘅問題。嗱，第一個問題即係若果個條件咧，任何將來任何一間嘅書行咧，
佢要即係做呢一類LPM或者有限法律責任嘅合夥。
嘅律師行嘅話咧，佢一定要登出呢個L.O.P.呢個字眼啦。
第二咧，亦都係保障翻有關啲公眾利益咧。佢哋依個要買咧額外嘅誒，即係專業賠償嘅保險，即係另外再要買多一千萬每一個，即係個個新索嗰度。咁所以呢個嚟講咧，就就會係呢一呢兩方面咧嚟到保障有關呢個消費者嘅權益。
佢知道你而家丟呢個，即係去一間律師行咧，佢係一間L.O.P嘅律師行，亦都有呢個誒額外嘅所謂嗰個。
誒保險嘅賠償就多呢個一千萬嘅，咁另外咧就至於講到話誒，另外有咩條件話作為一個所謂即係innocent partner，即係嗰個係清白又無辜嘅partner咧，佢係免受其他嘅所謂誒法律嘅責任咧。咁嗰度就喺呢個。
最主要喺翻我哋嗰個《Legal Petitions and Memorandums》咧，入邊有關嘅條文嗰度寫出嚟嘅。啊，咁嗰度其中其中有啲嘢咧，唔係話就噉話。你話一個只係無辜嘅partner噉就係冇事嘅。其中一個無作為你個無辜partner咧，你嘅證明咧，你哋都要採取合理嘅步驟。
嚟到監管有關於律師行處理嗰事務嗰度啊，你都要做咗出due diligence，噉你先至能夠可以作為呢個豁免呢個所謂有關嘅作為責任。
但係問題嚟講，始終嚟講，成間律師行佢本身都要承擔有關嘅法律嘅責任。如果佢有任務嘅，所謂專業嘅疏忽嘅嚇，咁所以作為一個消費者，一個客户。
佢由於專業疏忽導致佢有任何損失嘅。
佢會claim嗰間律師行，咁律師行我哋亦都講到咧。最初就有一個P.I.S.嗰個cover嗰度已經一千萬咧，另外再加埋L.O.P.有個top up insurance，另外多一千萬喺度嘅啊。咁咧呢個即係最基本咧，就起碼如果你你咧會有成差唔多二千萬咧，每一個claim cover。
而睇翻過往咧個claim嗰個歷史嘅嘅數字咧。
誒以前我哋啲起碼好幾年前咧上嚟立法會啲誒誒搜過有關嘅數字，但係今日我啱啱冇啲數字喺手。但係大多數嘅數字咧，嗰個claim咧係超過可以咁講，超過九成以上咧都係少過一千萬啊，即係個claim係少過一千萬。咁但係當然而家我哋做呢個所謂L。
咧，我哋都要畀呢個消費者額外一個信心，所以都有個top-up insurance，亦都同翻就新加坡同埋倫敦嗰邊咧嗰個即係海外嗰啲其他司法區咧係有個相比嘅，就係噉樣。係嗱，咁喺嗰個法律責任，我哋有刑事嘅法律責任，亦都有民事嘅法律責任啦。咁喺民事上咧。
啊，點樣為之你可能有一個合理嘅，即係你你due diligence，即係嗰個啊合理嘅，即係你自己都審查過你律師行裏邊可能嗰個啊機制啦。咁喺咩情況底下啦？喺呢度能唔能夠釐清到，即係減少訴訟嘅啫，即係嗰啲recourse liability你自己係咪有一啲嘢你根本係？
partner你就要喺合夥人，你就要咩㗎啦？呢個係民事嘅嗱，刑事我自己都認識有行家係真係其中一個partner，佢走去攞咗個客户嗰個誒存款去買樓，後屘啊蝕曬噉，跟住真係係變咗刑事。其中一個partner要坐監，但係佢咧就經過好。
好好長嘅官司，自己就甩咗嘅，但係要打官司嚇噉。所以你而家呢一度咧，你係似乎係想盡量咧，如果能夠清晰嘅有某一啲情況底下，就可能避免咗另外一個所謂無辜嘅合夥人，佢就可以唔使譬如誒承擔刑事嘅責任啦嚇。
或者甚至民事上咧，佢都未必要即係連帶去承擔嘅。咁呢一度係咪清晰咗咧？你認為即係有民事有刑事嚇兩方面可唔可以？因為呢一個其實係比較重要嘅問題嚟嘅。誒嗱，我只能咁講啦，即係答翻梁議員呢個問題咧。如果刑事嘅站大家知道咧，呢個基本。
常係個別嘅行為嘅嚇。如果譬如某一個partner，噉佢係真係話犯咗刑事嘅，譬如。
盜取咗客户嘅錢咁講啦，或者其他啲即係刑事嘅行為，咁應應該佢就個人要承擔嘅責任。
啊！你唔能夠將個刑事責任咧，亦都牽涉埋其他關到思考其他嘅partner嘅，除非其他partner亦都係有份啊！即係大家知道，譬如好似一個合謀噉樣啊，譬如咁講到即係最壞嗰啲。咁如果你係一個真係合謀嘅話，咁唔知係一一個畀一個partner啦，亦都喺合謀嗰個集團入邊嗰啲成員亦都會。
會有刑事責任啦，但係by and large，即係我哋睇法就話，如果純粹視為一個個人嘅行為嘅刑事責任，就係嗰位律師佢自己負責翻自己個人嘅行為嗰個嗰個刑事嘅責任，其他呢啲係無辜嘅，佢哋唔係參與呢個所以個罪行嘅，噉佢哋係唔會負上任何刑罰。呢個我哋嘅睇法。咁但係當然。
講翻到民事責任咧，你知通常民事嘅責任嗰堆就會誒，以前我哋即係知道話作為一個普通嘅合夥人制度general partnership嗰啲咧，就算你點樣清白啲好咧，你係會咧即係個別同埋啊，即係作為joint and severally liable咧，即係整體亦都要負責任。咁而一索我點，我哋引用呢個L.P.咧，就分清。
個界限。如果假如我有一個清白嘅partner咧，如果我真係冇過失嘅啊，知唔知噉我係唔需要承擔另外嗰個partner即係話有關嗰個即係民事上個疏忽嘅責任。咁如果又真係話，如果真係嗰位某個partner咧，佢真係有疏忽而導致有客户損失，所以變咗我哋都有呢個收益機制咧。
有個P.I.S.有一千萬嗰個嗰個賠償機制，亦都有個top不變shut，有另外多一千萬機制，總共二千萬就噉樣。嗯，嗱，誒，如果講疏忽啫，唔係故意，唔係刑事嗰啲㗎啦，佢真係疏忽。咁可能喺個機制裏邊咧，佢哋成間律師行佢設計個管理機制，可能有有啲容易係出咗問題噉。譬如喺個機
即係出問題嘅話咧，就唔係話其中一，淨係其中一個合夥人。
佢承擔責任。雖然嗰個case可能係佢去handle，但係可能你個機制總之中間唔知點樣啦嚇講到機制嘅話，噉你可能導致成間律師樓嘅疏忽啦。雖然有個case係佢負責，甚至有啲可能係律細律即係助理律師，好好簡單係嘛？噉你可能喺呢啲情況底下，係咪而家都嚟？
清到，因為老實講咧，對有啲個別律師嚟講，佢真係打工，佢跟足佢嘅機制，但係最後係可能有導致係誒疏忽嘅問題，噉就應該係個律師樓去擔啦，就唔係嗰個個別律師啦。有時你係嘛？我雖然用語言，你講得好好對啦，就係即係點解？如果你講個別嘅，譬如。
一個誒係受僱嘅律師一個assistant或者一個solicitor都一樣，咁通常間firm即係個principal即係會care嘅liability嘅問題啦，咁呢啲會就會found翻呢個PIS嗰個機制嗰度啦，係咪？噉就所以變咗嚟講咧，而家但係唔好唔記得，而家我哋講緊LOP咧就係講真係嗰啲。
partners之間partners個噉就即係你assistant solicitor同埋你consulting嘅commenter即係在employee嗰度咧，咁成個firm就會有有becare liable噉樣。O.K. O.K.咁即係即係我想問咧，有一點咧就係你哋即係呢個亦都係想喺呢一度我哋過，噉你就已經係最後stage。你哋律師。
會最初嘅倡議同而家嘅形式咧係有啲唔同嘅，係咪啊？可唔可以講翻？其實你哋覺得最即係個唔同係乜嘢嚇？我哋而家過咗呢個係咪其實都係過咗你哋想要嘅一半咧？即係你可唔可以講喺呢一度就一個記錄啦？
誒，如果梁議員如果你噉樣問我咧，呢個即係我要講咧，即係我做咗呢一個committee嗰度差唔多超過十年咧。當我哋有好多嘅感觸嘅，知唔知啊？啊，即係永遠大家知道人生嘅嘢。儘量簡短啦。係啦，我我我哋我哋希望可能誒，即係夢想希望達到嗰啲啊，但係知道實際上有啲係做唔到嘅，知唔知啊？
咁誒有好多掣肘，包括埋你即係誒律政司處啦嚇，同埋你啲有關施惠者嘅組織啦。另外，最後我哋上到嚟呢個立法會都係你議員，亦都係要考慮各方面公眾利益。係，所以變咗而家我哋咧做出嚟而家呢個L.O.P.呢一個所謂呢個model咧，嗱，我只能夠講咧，如果以。
以我心目中講咧，如果我心目中係十分係達到我滿意嘅，全部滿意分咧，我哋可能真係一得五分到。係啊係啊，我知道係。咁但係呢個我哋唯有即係接受呢個現實啦。啊，即係問題，起碼咧呢個主要個《Mandolinisa》即係二零一二年已經已經係通過咗㗎啦。係，咁而家我哋三年咧，你諗？
嘛，嗰啲嗰個。
個進展啊，都相當緩慢。點解又要考慮呢啲所謂呢啲subsidy legislation，又要再過幾關噉嘅問題？咁所以我哋希望而家真係希望大家要誒立法會議員亦都能夠咧提供個方便咧，我哋都希望即係話盡早能夠喺出年一月一號真係能夠實行呢樣嘢，所以。
好多嘅law firm，即係我哋個同業都希望話盡快有啲L.O.P.新呢家，而家都睇翻美國嗰邊咧，人哋講緊一九九零年已經有，我哋其實已經係廿幾年之後先至話啊追趕翻或者係同翻你歐美啊啊其他啲即係啊即係先進啲嘅法律體係嗰啲。
看齊。
好，唔該曬。
如果冇其他委員有問題咧，誒，我哋誒可以就係進入。
嚇，逐節審審議。
咁咧，誒標的文本係誒CB四一二六八一四一五。
咁其實誒，法律顧問，你有冇咩嘅特別嘅comment？
嚇！噉我睇完之後，我都冇乜特別嘅誒咩意見，唔知道委員有冇？
如果冇嘅話咧，誒秘書，你不如講講嗰個。你都唔需要逐個睇，我哋都用逐條睇。如果委員，如果委員覺得有需要先。
我哋族業，你講好咗。
冇。
係啊！我哋睇曬。
謝偉俊，我若果我唯一誒想提提就係嗰個七十三大A嗰度咧，就關於LPO入man咗啦，咁然後有個。
provision is there while the council may make interim rules, which make provision for the better carrying out of section seventy eight.
Capital D。
誒，我想瞭解下嗰個誒嗰啲provisions，obviously係因為empowering section咧，畀law society可以比較一個flexibility去處理問題。但係red誒喺喺依個階段，你哋有冇乜嘢誒初步嘅諗法，關於呢個誒再所謂誒？
呢類嘅provisions即係關於seventy ad seventy ad嘅provisions。
初步。
其實誒，我哋而家嗰個誒，嗱誒，limitation related partnerships top up insurance rules就係根據頭先你講個section去做嘅。
嗯哼。
哦，所以而家我哋而家其他其中個rules而家就係presumed to呢個section seventy three A cap A，所以我而家制定咗seventy A D係咪？而A D就係我哋而家喺個包裏邊嗰嗰啲噉嘅rules嚟嘅。OK， thank you very much。就如果你請睇翻你而家append嗰度咧，就係嗰個and and mixture two嗰度係mixture two。
那就會畀佢，連接第二個，就set up個limit line，畀佢punish，top up insurance rules。
一 mixture two。
如果你睇翻就right hand side度咧，未見到有寫part two嘅。
Top-up insurance under Section 7A of Ordinance。咁exactly而家我哋呢個top-up insurance咧就係make under呢個Section 7A of Amendment Ordinance。
I see.
Right. Thanks very much. Thank you. 好啦，咁即係基本上咧，所有將來嘅L.O.P咧。
如果佢哋要買top-up insurance咧，佢哋一定要啊誒透過呢一個香港即係。
誒授權嘅所謂嘅保險公司嚟到購買呢個保險啦，或者英國嘅Lloyds啦。
或者係一個所謂association underwriters approved by the insurance authority。
呢三類，咁即係話唔係話試過，好似喺英國咧，佢出現有啲問題咧，有啲人買咧所謂誒professional family insurance咧，佢買啲可能即係海外註冊嘅公司嘅地方嗰度咧，咁然後到將來有咩要要求賠償嗰陣時咧，發現間保險公司咧，可能即係冇實際嘅資產，同埋又喺外外嗰陣時你好難追討。
咁所以我哋已經有個要求咧，就一呢啲保險公司如果發呢啲咪保單嘅話咧，一定要香港嚇喺香港授權嘅保險公司，或者內申同埋呢個Association Underwriters Approved Insurance Authority。咁相對嚟講，我哋認為咧，亦都係保障到消費者嘅權益。
誒呢個我理解咪應該同翻non-LP farm嘅情況都係類同嘅，即係因為我其中我個section我見到係關於呢個LP嘅farm嘅insurance嘅terms咧，就應該同non-LP farm係應該係similar。
個情況係咪噉樣？
Foreign lawyers嗰啲。
啊！誒，如果可能誒，即係謝元，我諗你係指係一個方方即係law firm㗎啦，local firms啊，唔係local firm。local firm我哋通常我哋有個P.I.S.㗎嘛，我哋有professional indemnity insurance咧，就基本上每一個律師咧或者律師行咧，佢哋每年咧要畀個再個contribution個保保保費。
係咯，畀咗呢個即係。Sorry，對唔住我，我我我剛先一個top up insurance個aspect。哦，就top up insurance係咁呢個咧，我哋會一視同仁，無論local firm同埋foreign firm，大家一模一樣嘅。Right， OK，我哋都係咁講嚇，即係我哋一定要大家一定一個level playing field啊，所以我哋冇話歧視任何海外或者本地嘅firm。Thank you。
好。
麗美婚宴。
我冇具體嘅意見㗎啦，我覺得差即係自交對呢個成熟，但係我係一點要求啫。誒，因為其實公眾嚟講對U L P啊或者咩，佢唔一定好清楚嘅。你話個招牌裏邊打咗，我希望你哋咧喺呢個法例生效之後做少少咧公眾推廣嘅工作，起碼佢係認識原來係有。
誒兩類嘅承擔責任嘅，因為呢個係一個轉變，噉係比我哋嘅公眾更加清楚去選擇做消費者嘅時候，好冇誒？梁元，你講得絕對係正確嘅。我哋啱啱正喺出邊喺度等嘅時候咧，我哋都傾到點樣嚟到推動呢個所嗰個教育同埋宣傳嘅工作。咁所以點解我哋要諗住？
咧就要出年一月一號咧，就起碼我哋有有有五個月或者六個月嘅時間咧，就去計劃，唔止話推廣畀公眾等佢知道L.O.P同埋普通嘅General Policy有咩分別咧，同埋我哋都要教育翻同埋。
我哋自己個個會嘅會員，新啲緊有啲會員，你都想參與呢個做呢個L.O.P，係咪？佢哋都知道個個分別係點樣，同埋有咩個top insurance嘅嘅嘅要求嗰啲嘢。咁所以我哋會一定唔會放鬆下。嗱，你哋可能放submissive咧，但係我哋嘅secretary繼續要做嘢，即係已經講咗啦，知唔知？
啊好，你我哋雖然嚟放放暑假啫，但係真係唔係放假嘅。嗰啲冇得放，唔緊要，最緊要做好嗰個公眾嘅嚇，以免有投訴啦。咁如果委員冇其他問題咧，啊誒，我請請啊秘書講一講嗰個時間表係點樣及未來。
未來即係如果我哋審議完畢咧，噉我哋就會十月九號就有個書面嘅報告咧，就交翻畀內會嘅。
咁跟住咧，咁誒咁誒，即係因為我哋已經已係延展呢個審議期咧，就去到誒下一個會期嘅第一個立法會嘅大會。咁而家已經定咗喺十月十四號。咁如果我哋誒將呢個書面報告交去內會，如果議員咧係需要有修訂咧，就可以畀呢個五個。
個整天嘅嘅嘅notice咧，就可以咧就做個修正。即係預期，即係簡單啲講，預期就係我哋十月十四號咧會通過大會。咁誒，我相信你喺誒二零一六年一月一號想生效嗰個目標咧，應該係完全冇問題嘅。嗯。啊。
好。
啊，咁如果誒冇其他，仲有冇其他嘢？冇其他嘢，噉我宣佈今日會議結束，多謝大家。